<topics>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-boston-subway</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024441/1897-03-04/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=Boston+Dead+dead+explosion+flame+gas+Gas+Subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Escaping Gas in Boston Subway
Works Great Havoc.
HALF A HUNDRED INJURED
PnsHlng Electric Cnr "Wrecked and
Adjoining Ituildiiigg Itadly Dam
aged Partial Liht of Dead and
Disabled Accident Occurred ut
Treuiunt and lloylbtoti Streets.
Boston, March 4. An explosion lias just
occurred in the subway excavation at the
corner of Trcraont and Ooylston streets.
Three electric cars that were passing
at the time were wrecked and one ot
them was burned. Several bulldingsin the
vicinity were more or less damaged.
The explosion was caused by escaping
gas.
Among the buildings damaged are the
Hotel Pclliam, the Knickerbocker and
Head buildings and the Masonic Temple.
Window glass in buildings within 200
feet of the scene of the explosion were
shattered.
At least twelve persons were killed.
Four bodies have been removed to un
dertaking' rooms.
Forty-two persons arc at the Emergency
Hospital.
Among the dead are:
Rev. W. A. Slack, professor at Tufts Col
lege. G. I. Bigclow, conductor.
Unknown man and woman.
The injured include James Reardon, John
J. O'Conuor, Thomas F. Ford, Mrs. J. R.
Wilson, Nellie Jackson, Lucy Dolan, F.
W. Tceling, and Mrs. F. A. reck
There seems to be no doubt thatatleast
eight persons were immediately killed.
The explosion came Jutt as the streetcars
were almost in the ceutcr of the space at
the corner.
The first car was In the center when the
explosion came. The whole of the wood
work, which is used as a bridge over the
subway, was lifted into the air, carrying
the first car with it and taking along the
two horses of the second car. The other
Tehlcles were lifted straight into the air,
but came down on the tracks. Instantly
the air was filled with flying debris.
The firat electric car, the one in which
most or the killed were riding, no sooner
reached the track than It broke in hair,
and the whole portion Immediately burst
into flame. Then someone sounded a fire
alarm. This brought a large rescue force
to the scene, and almost immediately calls
were being sent out hurriedly for the am
bulances. It was an awful Eight that met the gaze
of those who were first on the scene. In
the center was the long blazing electric
car. .Close beride this were the bodies ot
the two horses killed instantly, and about
ten, twenty, thirty feet away from where
the woodwork of the car was blazing lay
the dead and wounded people. Those who
wore not injured in the cars on Boylston
6treet were Incapable ot action
at first, and people in the buildings and
stores surrounding did not know what had
occurred, but it did not take them long
to secure their senses, and almost imme
diately there was a rush to the assistance
ot the wounded.
It is stated that there was not a person
on the three cars who was not injured, and
all the wounds received were severe. Im
mediately stores and offices were con
verted into temporary hospitals until am
bulances could arrive. 1 1 was a gruesome
spectacle to see these bodies exposed on
the sidewalks.
Hose carriages were pressed into service
as ambulances, and immediately they were
started on their humane duty or getting the
maimed to the hospitals.
It Is supposed that-one of the dead women
at Jones' undertaking rooms Is Mrs. A. M.
Bates. She was out wlth a sister this
morning and has not returned. The sister
returned home slightly injurcd</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1897-09-19/ed-1/?sp=32&amp;q=BOSTON+Boston+BOSTONS+SUBWAY+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>T1IK BOSTON SUBWAY PARTLY COM?
PLETED AND IN OPERATION.
A BRI0I1TI.T UOIITED Tl NNW. AFKfU'.PlN?: RAPID
TRANSIT FOR BLECTRIO CARS CONORS
TIO? OV TUB BTREET9 RELIEVBD,
The subway for streetcars In Boston, a pari
of whli h has Ju il b >a op? n? -i for at rvlce. is an
em.???? of more than local Interest The ne
eesslty for some relief t? the i rowded thorough?
fares above it can besl be appre? lat? d, of course,
by H lonlans; but tl?.- Modem Aib.n.s is i?; no
means th.ily cltj In this countr) which is
beset with problems of the same character.
ThofO who :ii" familiar v.iih "!h&lt;- lay of tiie
land" in Bosl? n remember thai Tremont-st. runs
In a ajenerall) north-and-aonth direction and
forms ihe istern boundary of th.- Common.
Ii i-; intersected by Rovlston-st., which consti?
tutes Ihe southern boundary of thai historic
parle On the Boylsl m and Tremonl st edges
of the Common there is a broad promenade.
known as the Mall. The main part of the sub?
ira. li. h Is w Id nough to a? commodate four
tracks, passes under ihe Tremonl st. Mall, and.
niter passing under Park-st, which lies along
the northern side if ine Common, extends mr
will extend, when completed) to Scollay ?Square,
thence eastward to Adams Square, ami finally
up northward again to Hayraarkel Square.
This terminus Is close to the great union rail?
way station .it the North End.
Ft en th.- oin, r of Tri mont and Boylston sts.
there are two extensions, wldn enough f>?r only
a double track. Boylston st. Mall for about '.k"> feet, and then
ascends an Incline through an op? n ul for ,'il*
feel The terminal station for this branch la
situated In th- Public Gardens. The other
branch reaches away to the southward, and. on
nearlng th<- Junction of Bhawmul ave. and Tn
mont-st., forks. A separate two-track incline
leads up into each of those streeta
Including th? Inclines, ihe subway has a total
length of about a mile and a half, und will con?
tain about five miles of track Al present the
branches from th.rn.-r of Boylston and Tre?
monl Bl.-. and th-- main line up to Park-Si. an
In operation. A great >l<-.il o? work has already
been done on the northern portion of the route,
arid it is h? i I thai everything all) be finished
within th> n \t eight months. Hi und wats
broken for the subway in April, 1805, twenty
Bine month- ago.
The depth of this underground passageway Is
1 I f. t. The Width IS L'i feel for I WO T.|. l(S, .11,d
18 feel f.-r f? ur. Al Int rvala of sis r- et, along the
side.-, si--. I posts are b< t up on at.1 foundatl >nB,
and from the tops of those on one side there
r? rn h a? n i to the top ..f o, i th? r
stul roof beams. Where there arc four tracks
there is a c? ntral lia.f posts in the turn I, In
addition to those along the sides, From one
ro i am t.? the n< sl th? re cxl nd an ai h of
ma t.ry. These su< Iv? ai hi f. mil I hi
roof, an covered with coni-rete; ind th?
mat? lal HI th? pace betWi'.-i
the Bides. A waterproof I
i In es iding from I .....a, wat< r that
other? leak n fi ml ill. Th? m i
?onry floor is d, like an Inv? rted ar. h,
an l al ng II ?rural line iher? r in i a dra n At
Int? r\ ala the train a pit, from
which, whem ver the wat? r rises to a
level, the contents arc withdrawn bj auti i il
ally con troll? I 1?. :r,,- pumps
V? ntllatlon Is ff? '.-l by hui i ?l irj ran
establish? d in masonrj it thi or four
pointa along the i ne. The air Is suck l out of
the subway, and forced upward thi ugh the
op nfnga to Ihe level of ihe ?trei-i, ll u dr< I of
Im and? m i ctrlc imi and scores of an
Hghta ai i advanl ig? i al ?ng Ihe in
terl? r. As clectrlelt) i>d for th?
propulsion of the i ara hi? h i il
th? r.- la i. smoke lo a? umulat? i n the -Mings,
and no foul gases to offend the fa i rv?i
Tin-re is no reason why th? pla h ..-1 n I r?
main lean, sweet and bright for years.
AI th? und? rground r irse, the
subway is broaden? I A high Air? fenc? runa
lengthwise In the middle, irallng the two
noi thboui -1 tr u from the tw?i soul hi un I.
The tra- lu of e.i., t, p.ur are Ivided i rial n
gineers call an "island platform." saj feel
wide, and 300 or IfSJ feel long. Ace? i.m tie
had to on? platform from the ??(her onlj b) pro
Ing down a low flight of ita ai i through a
narrow bul brightly Illuminated pas age undei
n- ath, oi i going up i the street and rosslng
iv? r.
The cara v. hi, h run Ihn ugh the tunnel ar- oi
("..i irj li lej cars, but, iik.- many which tra-.
i other rout? In t!:-- i ty, th? y are all con?
trolled by one ror|ioratliin, Ihe West Knd Street
Hallway Company, to which, by the way, the
subwaj la- lieen leased by th? Tran t Commis
i neri 'iii fact partially explains some of the
pri au ?i taken al the stations. Then one
buys a ii ki t In lure h >a riling i.u or Hing a,
rhan? e to do o, are) thi ndui lor on I h? car col
lecta Ihe Ll? kets, Kill fn m th? i tatlon i lat
Is effected Ihrouul lun les, wbi< b a.. >w
a person to pa In onlj ?in dh i ion.
in. id, easy stall rid d n n from Ih I reel
r? the und und statloi 'i i
more than thirty Btej In a (light Th ai
two flights for He northbound tracks, ind two
f ?r the Bouthl ?ui I The h ud of a li
i.; in loa d by a neat oni tory, gla
granite b ill lin Glazed white i?i i. i< and i I? lit)
?,f whit.- paint Impart to ihe station interlora
a fresh and the r> appearance. At present t?..-
BOSTON'S NEW SUBWAY INCLINE IN THE PUBLIC GARDEN.
?nly stations in use underground are at the cor
ner of Boylston and Tremont sts. ami at Park-st
A temporary loop at the latter point permits
the northbound cars to return without switch?
ing. When the subway is completed, however.
there uiii i.ther stations at Si o lay Square,
Adams Square and Hay market Square.
miy an engineer can begin to understand
th.- difficulties of an undertaking lik?- this
Count leas sewers, a ater-plpcs, gasplp? s and tele
phon? -Air.- conduits have been laid close to the
route, and Bom of ih.s,- have been bared dur?
ing the prigresa of the necessary excavation.
When ihelr position was at a higher level than
the r..of ,,f the future subway it was not neces?
sary to do ne re than lo protect them carefully
f.r the lime. Bui if the) were lower than the
roof, and higher than the Boor, the situation
was root, serious. Two great water mains, one
thirty Inches In diameter and the other forty
BOSTONS NEW SUBWAY FOUR-TRACK SUBWAY UNDER TRKMONT-ST.
Inches across, ?ere encountered at that very in
invenlent level, It became necessary to con
utru t siphons, bending down under the subway
and up agiln on the other Bide, in order to ad
ju-t these conflicts of Interest. Kor the happy
solution of all th.-:- difficulties great credit is
,'-j to th? t'ity Commission Intrusted with the
work, to their 'hlef ngli.r, and, in some meas?
ure, t. the engine, rs of the West End Company,
An Incidental l j: I mi orlant f. ature of tlie
plan of construction Is the avoidance of grade
i rossinirs. In the four-track passageway the
Iloylston-st. ears have the two inside tracks,
and the Tremont-st and Bhawmut-ave. ears use
the two outer ones in common. Accordingly,
at th" southeastern corner of the Common, the
westernmost track (southnound) is carried down
Under the two central ones, by a special one
track tunrnl which soon emerges With another
one-track tunnel carrying th>- up-track. At a
point still further south a similar plan Is pur
sued in th.- separating of the Bhawmut-ave. and
Tremont-st. cars
Tie- cipa. Ity of the subway is ninety cars
per mit,ute. Inasmui h as th" facilities thus af?
forded :ir.- Buppli mentary to th.me already af
forded on Tremont-st., and an- not a substitute
for the latter, a distinct increase In the number
of punes, as well as freedom from blockades,
bas been secured.
RJtlUYBRAVIVO POSTAI* CARDS.
i From The Boston Transcript.
An advertisement has appeared in some of the
daily papers In which a cosh payment has been
offered for uneancelled printed postal cards. It
seems that many business houses have occasion
j to have a large number of postal cards printed
to advertise some special line of goods or for
the use of some travelling man. For some rea?
son or other the conditions may change, so that
perhaps only half of the cards are use?), being
or m'.cd, Lbey can nut be used in any other way,,
j and the result is that in nine CSSSS out of ten
they are consigned to the waste basket, a? the
Government does not red. em uncancelled postal
cards an it does stamped envelopes.
A process has been discovered by which all of
the printed matter may be removed from the
card, leaving it in the same condition as when
bought at the poatofBcn. A charge of one-half
cent per card is- made for this work; or, in other
words, a man sends five hundred carda to be
"made over." The man who does the work
charges f?SO for his services, ami tin- u.?tomer
save? $1* ."?0, as the printed cards were of no uas
to him.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn95079490/1897-10-23/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=BOSTON+SUBWAY</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE BOSTON SUBWAY
SATISFACTORY SOLUTION OF THE
STREET CAR PROBLEM.
Contention of Trafllc In tli? Iluny Streets
of the Uub Relieved by Underground
Trolley Lines?Tunnels Tlmt Am Light,
Clean uud Attractive.
It is now possible to cross Tromont
street, Boston, at any point opposite tho
Common and at any time of day without
loss of life or limb. Tho new subway has
brought about tho change.
It 1 s an old tradition that tho fathers of
Boston, when thoy laid out tho city, let
the. streets follow the winding cow paths.
At any rate, the streets ius thoy exist today
urc very crooked and must of them aro
very narrow. This was all right in Revo?
lutionary times, but when the city grow
miles beyond tho Common und spread it?
self out to tho south and west; when busi?
ness centered itself along tbu lower ends
of Washington and Trentont streets, and
when dozens of street car tracks usurped
tho narrow roadways, then the Bostonlans
wished their ancestors bud not stuck so
closely to the cow paths.
Probably no other city on the continent,
was ever so badly allllctcd with a conges?
tion of trnllic as tho Hub haslieon for
many yea: Some of tho most important
street ear linen skirt tho south and east,
cornets ol the Common on Boylston mid
Tremont streets. When I he chango was
made hum hoc. epov.vr to trolley, matters
grew worse. Then tho poles and the tan?
gle of overhead wires made that historic.
breathing spot look liko a pieco of dingy,
green billiard cloth which had become fray?
ed and tuttered around the edges. So after
much wrangling in tho legislature and
courts it w;ls decided tu build the subway
and put the trolley cars underground.
A large portion of the work bus already
lieen accomplished and Boston is delight?
ed with the result. The first thing a Hus?
ton man asks a visitor from Now York,
Chicago or elsewhere is:
"Been through tho subway yet'/ Let's
see?you huven't one in your place, have
you?"
It is, in fact, a triumph of engineering
anil well worth a visit. Then! arc throe
open cut.s where tho trolley curs enter the
subway. One Is out on Tremont street
whore Shawmut avenue comes in. Hero
the tracks from each of those jmorough
fares dive into the tunnel. Another is In
the Public gardens, where the cars com?
ing down Boylston street take tho under?
ground tlip. The third is at tho northerly
end of the subway, just beyond-Hay mar?
ket square and in front of the new Union
terminal railroad station into which the
Fitchburg, Hoston und Maine, Eastern
und other roads run. Theru is u. loop hern
DOSTON'S NEW SUBWAY INCLINE IN THE Plin
LIC ns most of the t rolley lines inako it their
terminus, and, the subway being four
tracked, they disgorge their passengers
and take the back track up town.
Including the inclines or open onto, tho
subway has a total length of 1 miles and
will contain about live miles of track. At
present the branch down Boylston street
along the Common side and the main line
down Tremont to Park street are in oper?
ation. The Shawmut avenue branch and
tho northerly end of the main lino will be
finished within the next eight months.
Ground was broken for the subway in
April, 18115. The sum appropriated was
$7,ii(?0,000 and, wonderful to relate, tho
transit commissioners say that it is proba?
ble the cost will bo about $1,000,000 less
than that sum.
No groat difficulties have been encoun?
tered thus far in digging this big liplo In
the ground. Of course there were count?
less sewers, water pipes, gas pipes, electric
wire conduits and the like und some -III
inch water mains at an inconvenient level
proved rather hnrxl to handle, but n? un?
expected conditions arose to delay tho
work. The main trunk of the subway
runs under the wide walk or mall on tho
east side of the Common, anil when the
excavations were being made the bones of
hundreds of old Puritans were disturbed.
This raised a bowl of righteous Indigna?
tion,and the sncredness of the long forgot
burying ground was harped upon for
weeks. Hut the commissioners quieted
the reverent patriots by collecting nil tho
bones and roiuterrlng them in the holy
ground of the Common, with a nice monu?
ment to mark the spot.
The tleepest jioint of tho subway is on
Boylston street, where the south bound
t racks are laid lit) feet lielow the surface,
but the average depth is 14 feet. The tun?
nel itself is a giant bore with ribs of steel
mid casings! of cement, asphalt, concrete
and masonry. The roof is a series of
arches und the floor Is concave, with
drains at the bottom. As tho drnins are
below the level of the sewers, jilts have
been established at Intervals, and when
thev are filled with water automatic elec?
trical pumps are started, which empty
them Into tho sewers above.
Perhaps yon imagine that Boston's sub?
way is a tlark, damp, ill smelling place. It
is nothing of the sort. The entrances to
the stations aro handsome structures of
stone, with glass roofs. The only fault, to
be found with them is that thev remind
cs?blc. It makes food shortened
it i3 uahcaltb.ru! and filled with
icd by every medical r.::d culi- B
1
vegetable oil is nutritive, digest-
i
coil. Itisnu
:d with or fried
armful results.
md yoll^w tins,with
u((nM-/ililii( urc.il??
way. lladounlyby
1 PAN Y,
Montreal. ^?-?n?? _^ff* fa
you or an olo Urccinn tomi)?ft" least that
is what I thought of the first time I saw
one. Put then you go down an easy (light
of wide stone steps to n cheerful, brilliant?
ly lighted station. Everything Isdazzllug
ly white. The bricks lining the entrance
art? of glazed white porcelain, the mason?
ry arches are painted white and the iron
pillars and supports arc covered with im?
maculate white; enamel. Incandescent and
are lights Hash everywhere, and the vista
nhead through tho stretches of the subway
is far from u dingy one. It. Is about tho
cleanest und neatest holu In tho ground in
existence and no doubt will be kept so.
Already lifo tralllo on Tromont and Duyl
ston streets has been much decreased, ami
when tl;e subway is fully completed Bos?
ton foil: may get about their town with
comparative ease und safety.
ALKKKD U. ROWLEY.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1897-12-15/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=BOSTON+Boston+SUBWAY+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>'BOSTON'S UNUSED SUBWAY.
ft) H' VMDBnOltOVSD TBAXBITA TAILURE
j jjv oxvU x. rjtA otice.
Ij aYeople Reniie ta L'se It. Jot as Thfir Wonld
.1' the Hot la tbo Cronna Transit rropwed
J'v fbr Wew .rk Only Keren Per Cent, ef the
M Total Tronic Credited ta the flatmar The
j rreniable rnney TraDI o Lost to It Entirely
Jf Vat tba Condlllem Are nl Farorablr
BbS. Beaten Want, an Klevatrd nallraad Hon,
'sflf "H Before any farther attempt la mado to com'
i V Bait tbli eltr to the building of the proposed
jH underground system of rapid tranalt it would
H be well for every ono Interested to learn somo-
ll thing of the experience which Boston Is now
I lusTlng with Its subway. Boston's subway Is
li'H New York's proposed underground railroad In
L S miniature, excopt that It was constructed for
I H the use of the trolley car lines Instead of being
I V equipped with cars, motors, and power of Its
I H own, and mnnlnir two sets of trains one express
tf( I and one local.
The Boston subway short. That part now
jkVM tense Is less than ft mile In length, and the
KS farts which are under construction or proposed
R M Would add only about another mile to the tun
Hk wr Bet, There lr, perhaps, no finer specimen of
Jl&B passenger tunnel work any whero In the world,
aBfYS n ls doubtful -f anymore perfect tunnel
HtjH could Deconstructed.
B9p The tunnel runs under Tremont street, and
HHk Its extensions are to go under Cornhlll, Han
JJ. oxer street, and Washington streot, passing
i right through the denso business and shopping
districts, and thus securing every advantage
I that a road might have If It ran through Broad-
jf Tray, Fourteenth street and Twenty-third street,
i and part of Sixth avenue. And yet. In the face
j ef all these advantages, three months' experi
ence has shown that the Boston subway is not
popular, that people will not go Into It ex-
cept when they have to, and that the subway Is
lv a failure, save so far as It was a necosslty to re-
i'i Have the congestion of traffic on the street.
V XEED OF TUB BUDWAT.
A Bostonlans are proud of the subway. They
ri take strangers to see It, just as they take them
h to see Bunker IIIll Monument; make them ride
vM the length of It back and forth, and call alien
s' I tlon to all its fine foatures and then they keep
I away from it themsolves. Just as thoydofrom
if the monument. That this result ls of tntorest
I V to New Yorkers there can be no doubt. Tho
building of tbo subway growoutof a publloneed
Tfhloh was as absolute and pressing as the need
v ef this city for some addition to Its trafllo
in. facilities.
Hien, about ten years ago. the West End
oet Railway Company began to transform tho
horso car lines of Boston Into electric trot
lines the narrow streets In tho heart of
iton were already choked with tho dally rush
vehicles. Boston has to-day tho most ex
stve and comprehensive electrlo car system
the world. The added cars which wero re
red for tho now service fairly filled
i streets of the little central city
ere they were all concentrated. These
lines eorvo a suburban population of
trly a million persons, and it is possible to
;e a car for any part of the territory covered
.hoot going more thai a quarter of a mllo In
i city. Under a special act of the Lcglsla
e the Boston Transit Commission was ap
nted to devise a suitable means to relieve the
Station.
THE OrERATIVB COWTnAOT.
fader this commission tho subway wns
nned and is being built. Tho city of Boston
s for it and leases it to tho West End Street
llway Company for twenty years at an an
il rental which is not to be less than 4Ts per
it. upon the net cost of the tunnel, or more
,n .Ts per cent, upon tho sum of $7,000,000,
he tunnol should cost so much, and tho com
ly agrees to pay. in llou of interest, a toll of
nts for each car that passes through the
way. In caso the aggregate of tolls should
:eed the interest charges. The railroad com
ly cares for it, lights it, ventilates it, ana
ips It free from wator. i
fork was bosun on the subway on March 28,
13, and on Sept. 1 of this rear the first scc
o was put Into use. A second socllon was put
o use on Sept. 30. The main part of tbo sub
y now in use lies usdor Tremont street, bo
sen Park street and Boylst:n street. This
lion 'Is 1,700 feet long and contains four
cks. At both ends aro stations, built
nmodlously under ground and approached
m the surface by wide, easy stair
ye. wulch are protected by small or
mental stone buildings. At the BoyI
in street station the tunnel divides into
o two-tracked sections. Ono of these con
ues under Tremont street for about 1,200
it, whon its comes to tho surfaco and empties
cars upon the tracks in Tremont street and
awmut avenue, which hero diverge. The
ler branch turns sharply to the wostward,
asunder the edge of tho famous Common, to
Public Oarden beyond Ohnrles street, where
comes to tho surfaco, 1,200 foet from the
ylston streot station, and its cars goon tholr
y down Boylston street,
man standahd or coxsTitucnos.
The tunnel Is kept almost as light as day
im end to end. At the stations It ls lined on
sides with enamelled white brick. Through
t its length and on tho codings at tho
itlons It Is pnlnted white. At tlio su
ns and through the tunnol electric
hts aro hung In abundance, and to make
re that these shall not all fall at any ono tlnio
5y are divided nnd fed by two scparato clr
Its of wire, resides these lights, fixed In the
itnel, are the lights In tho passing cars, which
kept lit In making the tunnel passage. As
oorthreocarsaro passing In each direction
ery minute almost all the tliuo, their lights
me would keep it fairly well illuminated.
People doclare that they found the tunnel ro
ishlngly cool during the warm woather In Sep
nber Just after it was oponed, and In cold
lather they find It warm. No winds penetrato
and the moraont a porson gets to tho stairs at
itatlon he Is out of rench of storms. Only ono
jrce of discomfort has yet developed In tho
e of the tunnel, and that. It U belloved,
11 be remedied. This was, for the tlmo
lasted, a very groat trouble. It occurred
it month, when there had been a sudden
ange of 25 or 30 degrees in temperature,
oweathorhad been cold for thrco or four
ys, and the ground and tho Inside of tho tun
Ibadgotchillod until It was pretty nenrly as
Id under ground as on the surface. Thcncume
isoln tlio general teniperaturo of 23 or 30
grees. Tbo warm air. drawn Into tho tunnol
the ventllnting fans, struck against the
lllod roof and sides, and Immediately every
log began to weep. The cold roof and sides of
e tunnel condensed tho moisture In the
irraer air, and In a short tlmo the
jole Interior glistened with molsturu.
the stations tho condition was worst nnd pro
ced much discomfort. Here the air entered,
dof course gavo tin the greater part of its
ilsture. Most of tho moisture collected on tho
ling nnd dripped dnujion thn waiting passen
rs. People who had loft pleasant neathar
stairs found themselves exposed to trick
m streams below. It wns so bad that tbo
llroad company sot men to work scrnp
K down the roofs and Bides with riihbcr
urezers to gut rid of tho moisture. Even
this troiiblo cannot bo cured, tbo mil
sd officials do not believe that It would prove
serious consequence, bcciuso thero aro not
aro than thrco or four duj s In a year when
angrs of tetnpernturo uro wldo enough to
oduco tho drip.
REFL'SALOr THE run MO TO I'BK IT.
rho portion of (ho Bubnnyi use nt tlio pros
tllmo Is open fortrnvel from OoYlocl; A. M.
12 midnight cturlni; cwli day of tlio Muck.
lorenro at present 1,302 trips per duy being
n through ttio subway.
Vet hero Is the Bignilleaut fact; n study of tint
lly travel In tho Hiibnn-.. hour by hour and
y by day for months, Khiincd conclusive!)-, In
o judgment or tho,o who arc mont closely cou
nted, that the sub.va) U nut piipulnr.nm! that
Vf porsons tuo It, except w hen thev hnotn.
'esldcnt Littlo declares that this is aiiuuli
oro serious mutter than It would upniar to tliu
Initiated,
j THE KAKOV TIIAKKIO AVOIIIH IT,
B "In tho rush hours," he said, recently, In ills
jBA cussing tho matter, "I hit people in list tnke
HI every means of coiio)nnco that I here is at
t I hand. In these hours they Dock Into tlio sub-
Fii way as freely us they do In tliu ears i mining on
K, the surface, and during these hours nn carry
eH'-l about as many In the subway as It U possible
tJi for us to handle Iheront tboprnsotit time,"
Mf Then Mr. Little made a ntntument of which
iKmt. every street railway must reioi;nUo the truth,
lyK'l!, and which should bo inrrfiilly lonn.dered by
I M I.', every capitalist who maybe Invited to becomo
H I interested in building and operating the pio-
IbH posed rapid transit line In this city, provided tho
scheme ever gets so far as inviting contracts,
Thlsrushbourtraftlc,"Mr.Llttlocontlnued,
HkLSF "Is, however, not the business which wo mako
mv' tar money out of. If we had nothing but this
ntmi y other strlotly business traffic, it would
m
UK
b?id.1l!!,eH!.tA?i1B,lko Win business. Boring
nil tho middle part of earn day wo should bo
iu'inlf.,lSttsri!w "na (rotting nothing for
doing It. The fancy trnfUo 1s what wo want
and rely upon tho poople who ride bocauso Itls
V..VH nt to o, not bocauso they have to.
M? nTa. lhe People, our statistics show, who
will not go Into tho.subway. Wo know Just
how mnny persona tako tho cars In thn subwar.
becnuso wo sell tickets there beforo the peoplo
go upon tho station platforms, and these tickets
nro i-pllectcrl In tliocnrs. The sales of subway
car tlckcta show that thn tunnol gets a fixed
portion of the general trafllo, but docs not get Us
share of tho fluctuations,
Dlfll.tKK OF TIIF. 8UIIWAY IK ntiUItKS.
Wo carry nearly 200,000.000 pass-liners
every yoar. In September wo tarried 18.310,
(MX) passengers. Tho loop to tho Public Garden
from tho Park streot station was tho only ono
inon through tho subway during that month.
Tho atibwny trrtvel then wan 0.0 per cent, of
our wholo travel. In November, with tho Tre
mont streot and Shnwmul avenue toop open,
theMilnvnytraUIo reached 7.1 per cent, of tho
vtliolo,
"Sw His ft curious fact that although our
total number of passengers was Increased 111
October by 238,000 over the September figures,
tho number carried In tho subway was Increased
by only 7.000. Thfct great general tncronse was
nlmo-it entirely marto up of tho sort of fancy
riding 1 spoko of. Theio aro the peoplo who
Jump on n car nnd rldo downtown, ostensibly
to buy a spool of thrond or a skein of silk or
ynrn. hut really bocauso tho car Is handy and
the rldo pleasant. Theso pooplo won't go Into
the subway. If for no othor reason than becnuso
thoy won't walk down tho stairs.
"Tho steady trafllo which the tables show wo
can count upon ls shown In this table of a day's
sales of tickets on Oct. 1,"
Mr. Llttlo produced this tablet
rABSENOEns CARRIED IN BCBWAY OCT. 1, 1B07.
lloun. four.
a. M. r.
Oto 7. ill 7 4 to B S,0(IB
7 to t !A oto fl 3,408
8 to 0 S14 A to 7 l.nil
UtolO otlU 7 to S OIH
10 to 11 870 Hto V 096
11 to II! l.OUfi Oto'.O DID
r, M. lOtoll 44",
ito i l.nnintou: 247
1 to S I.K25
Oto 3 1,090 Total IS.SU7
ato 4 l.Kocl
AVOIDED EVEN MOKE IN STORMY WEATIIER.
One thing to be seen from theso Ilguros," Mr.
Llttlo added, Is that tho sulmny, although It
runs pistn number of the principal theatres,
does not get any appreciable quantiij- of that
strictly fancy riding, tho people going homo
from tbo theatres, any more than It gets the
sboppors.
On rainy days ono would suppose that tho
subway would get n bigger proportion of trafllo
than in flno weather; but this ls not true. I
mot Mr. Dalton. ono of tho Transit Commission,
the other day when It wns mining, at tho en
trance to tho Park street station.
'"Isn't this chnrnilngl' he exclaimed as he
got In out of the storm.
"I admitted th-it It was; but when I camoto
look over tha tables of daily receipts and com
pare thom with the total tralllo I found that
although tho general trafllo had fallen off less
than 0 per cent, because of tbo rainy dny, tho
subway traffic had lost 30 per cent. This Is the
rooro significant from tho fact that one
half the former number of cars nro now oft tho
streets above."
A reference to tho dally tablos showed how
tho travel In the subway fell off In unpleasant
weather. On Nor. 2, when tho usual dally
Irrffllc was 22,000 or 23,000 persons, only
14.000 went through tho subway. On Nov. 2a
tho number roll to 13,000, while tho next dny It
roso to 24,000. On Sundays, when tho tratllc
on nil parts of tho system ls fancy riding prin
cipally, tho number of passongers who go
through tbo subway falls as low as 0,000.
FACT8 FOR NEW YORK TO 1-0NDER,
These aro tho facta. If It wcro possible to
build tbo long tunnel proposed for this city nnd
mal.o all parts of It ns perfect ns tho Boston
subway, which is at least doubtful, what would
be thn effect of an oqual Indisposition of Now
Yorkers to using it upon tho chances of Its pay
ing I Tho proposed road would have enough to
contend with through tho location of its main
linos out of tho way of tho short-ride local
business, out of which alone profit ls to
be made; but If the fancy traffic avoided It, ns
It avoids the lloston subway, tho result would
bo ruinous, Tho contractors would find them
selves with no ono to carry except tho people
who wanted to ride to Harlem and far above
or to Klngsbrldge, all for fire cents, and. what
ever forfeit they had to make, they would soon
abandon tho lino for thn city to operate at a loss.
CACHES OF rUPLIC PREJUDICE.
Why the peoplo avoid tho subway Is a ques
tion much discussed. Perhaps as good nn ex
planation ns anr Is to bo found in a conversa
tion which took place between Tun Sun re
porter who gathered these fncts nnd the pretty
&lrl who Owns the news stnnd at one of Boston's
est hotels.
"Ilavo you beon through the subway yet I"
ho asked enthusiastically.
"Yes," the reporter nnswored.
"I have just been through It, Isn't It grand!"
she exclaimed.
"l)o you go through it of ten I" asked tho re
porter curiously.
"Ob, no!" Bho answered. "I think It's beau
tiful, so light, and dry, and comfort bio: but I
always take a surfaco car. I think I hate to
walk up the stairs, although I am not lazy. I
walk clear out to ltoxbury and back almost
ever' day, and have lost slxteon pounds by
doing so, but, somehow, I don't llko to go up and
down stairs In tho subway."
It ls probably something more than this thnt
deters people from going underground even In a
tunnel bo well lighted. It is well known thnt
the underground roads In London do not pay,
nnd this ls duo largely to tho lack of tho fnncy
trafflc, such as overflows surface lines and ele
vated roads In New York. Ask a Londoner If
he uses tho underground roads in his own city
much, and IiIb answer Is almost suro to bo:
"Oh, yes, but only when lhavo to."
NOW BOSTON WANTS AN ELEVATED ROAD.
That Boston has awakened to the fact that
subways arc not n good thing whero they can be
avoided. Is clear from the character of tho very
latest move now on foot there. This ls to build
elevated railroads from tho ends of the subway,
nnd thus, in thoopen air, enrry tho cars out be
yond the thickly built-UD sections to Rnx
bury, Cambridge, Cbarlestown, and be
jond. This plan ls to be carried out ns
soon as tho Stato Railroad Commission agrees
to a lease of the West End road's lines to the
new elevated railroad company.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016413/1901-07-24/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Boston+subway</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-06-21/ed-1/?sp=42&amp;q=BOSTON+subway</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1904-05-08/ed-1/?sp=57&amp;q=New+subway+York</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085947/1904-10-27/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=NEW+OPENED+SUBWAY+YORK</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87060004/1905-01-19/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=BOSTON+Boston+SUBWAY+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>ANOTHER BOSTON SUBWAY
Eat Ilpnlon Tunnel Junt Openti
IllliiM Under Itnrbor
Boston the pioneer city of America
In subway construction now boasts a
subway Maid to be the greatest single
boring yet completed under the enter
of a river or harbor It Is tho EnSt
Boston tiinnl extending from tile
zing UA8T JtOSTON TUNNEL
city proper under the harbor to
Maverick square East Boston It Is
the second subway to be opened In
Boston wns begun In 1000 has cost
3000000 and has Just been turned
over to tint Boston EIu rated Rallwny
company for operation It Id about
one ones twofifth miles In length and
has an exterior diameter of nearly
thirty feet thoilgli the thickness of
the walls bring Its Interior diameter
down to about twentyfour feet
The East Boston tunnel nets to n
depth of more than ninety feet below
tho waters of Boston harbor through
n blue day sediment It Is fov the
use of regulntlpn trolley cars which
come to the surface at the suburban
end of tilt passage nnd continue their
Journeys over tliestrce trucks Kven
trashy the tuba Vlll be connected di
rectly with the present Ruiwny In Ba
tons congested dlflUlct</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84023296/1906-06-09/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=bomb+Bomb+Boston+explosions+FIRE+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>FIRE IN SUBWAY.
Lives Impcrilled in Boslon's
Underground Railway.
Terrlflc Exploslona Caused by 8hort
Clrcultlng of Heavlly Charoea uiec
trlc vyirea Hundreds of Men and
Women Thrown Into Panlc Three
Persons Injured.
Boston A dull, low ronr, llko tho
blast of n chnrge of dynnmlte under
tona of grnnlte, nnd clouda ot black,
Blckenlng smoko belchlng fortli,
threw hundreds of men nnd women
into a panic nnd paralyzed trnfflc ln
the subwny nt the Boylston street
statlon at 5.30 o'clock, Wednesday af-
ternqpn
No one know the trouble. Elevatcd
road employes and offlclals were allke
confused, and fearful of what mlght
come next, fla tho smoko raphlly fllleil
tho stntloim at Boylston and Park
streets, nnd passengers wers rushed
from tlie cars to the surfacc.
Tralnmen nnd statlon pollce at
tempted to call the flrd departmont
and found tho telephones so charged
wlth clectrlclty as to be useless.
Mnny of the women reachlng the
subway by the Boylston street cars
were overcomo by the smoko, falnted,
nnd had to be dragged to the surfnce.
Several becanio hysterlcal and woro
controlled wlth much dimculty, the
danger belng constant of Bomeono
falllng from tho platforms overcome
by tho smoko and becomlng electro
cuted upon the deadly thlrd rall.
Tralnmaster Benjamln wns the flrst
offlclal to reach the Boylston street
statlon and to brlng some sort of or-
der out of tho cliaos. Enterlng the
subway along the llne of the north
bound cars he made hla way some 100
feet to the south of tlie statlon and
found the cause of the trouble.
The feed cables for the thlrd rall,
runnlng between the ralla and en
closed ln four-inch wooden box con
dults, were found grouuded and
throwlng off flashes of electrlclty,
whlch llluminnted the subway for
tnany hundreds of feet. The electrl
clty had jumped to other cables run
nlng parallel, and even charged the
wnlla of the subway. Ten powerful
cables felt the lnftuence of the crosn
nnd were cracklng nnd throwlng off
flames and flashes of llght, threaten
Ing death to any who cnme near.
Tho wooden box condtilt, black and
greasy and very Inflammable, was
burnlng rapldly. A north bound traln
whlch had passed over the spot got
nflro nnd wna inillod bnnk lo Waont
street, hlnzlng flercely underneath.
Tlie terrlfled passengers were hnnied
ntt nt Plpnsnnt Rtreet nnd tlie flro be-
nnivth tho. Kttn"gulshed by'road
employes before serlous damage was
done.
Three persons were hurt, nnd all of
them were on the surface. The nccl
dents whlch caused thelr Injurles were
the dlrect result of the trouble In tbo
subway. The Injured wero all near
the Pleasant street entrance to tho
Biibwny and were hurt by the explo
sions in three mnnholes at tliat polnt.
Tralnmaster Benjamln ordered all
tralns Into statlons, and then the cnr-
rent on the thlrd rall and feed cables
was shut off.
Chlef Mullcn and the flre depart
ment hod been notlfled before tho
power was shut off and entered tho
nubway nt the Boylston street sta
tlon, although there was great danger
for anyone, however famlllar ylth the
subway, to enter ln tlie dense smoke
whlch flllcd every foot of space be
tween the walls.
As Chlef Mullen's men toucbed the
walls thoy felt a shock at once. The
brass nozzle of the chemlcal hose
Ihey carrled became charged, and wlth
electrlclty runnlng up thelr arms the
men hcsltated for a mlnute for orders
from thelr chlef.
rlsk It," shouted Chlef Mull
en, and he dashed Into the smoko
filled subway. Hla men followed close
behlnd, thelr hands on the shoulders
of the men In front. A few darlng
newspaper men brought up the rear.
Half an hour was consumed ln put
llng out the flames whlch had fol
lowed nlong the box condults nearly
300 ynrds.
Both Chlef Mullen and Aaslstant
Chlef Brady termed It one of the
most dangerous flres they were ever
called upon to hnndle, not from lts In
tenslty but for the dangers of electro
cutlon that surrounded them and the
thlckness of the smoke.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1914-11-12/ed-1/?sp=2&amp;q=boston+subway</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020358/1897-02-11/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=boston+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BOSTON'S FAMOUS SUBWAY
CHIEF EXUlXliKK CAHSOX 3BI.IS
HOW IT IS COXSTIIVC1HD,
Lecture Before Engineers' Club Feature
of the Kuglnoeiiiig Work on the Subway
Subways In Other Cities.
An exceedingly Interesting and valu
able lecture was given last evening In
North Sheffield hall by Howard A. Car
son, member of the American Society
of Civil Engineers and chief engineer
of the famous Boston subway. The
lecture was given, under the auspic&i
of the Engineers' club and was largelj
attended by citizens as well as stu
dents. Professor DuBols Introduced Mr. Car
son, who spoke on "Subways in Bos
ton, London and Elsewhere." The lec
ture was illustrated by stereopticon
views of the Boston subway and also
of some of the European subways
which Mr. Carson has visited.
The lecturer at the commencement
explained why the Boston subway was
built. "The DODulatlon of Boston 130
years ago was less than 22,000; 100 years
ao about 26,000; In 1830, in the remem
brance of many, about 82,000, while to
day the city has about 600,000. The
population of Boston doubles In about
thirty-five years.
"The use o the streets for travel In
creases faster In proportion than the
population of the city. In 1896 167,000,000
persona were carried by the street rail
ways. While the population doubles
only in twenty-flve years, travel on the
street railways doubles In about ten
years.
"The streets are no wider now than
they were one hundred years ago, and
they are not able to do the work they
are needed to do. If streets can't do
the work required of them the natural
thing to do is to build them wider or
make new streets, but the cost is too
great for this, costing perhaps $100 a
foot. If you can't Wld or.broaden the
old streets you must do the way a per
son does when a house la overcrowded
and has not land to build new by add
ing stories to the old. In the case of a
street you have to decide between an
elevatedway or a subway.
"The mere cost of erecting an elevat
ed road is only about one-half or one
third of that of a eubway, but the dam
age which has to be paid to adjacent
property owners makes the cost of the
two systems about the same. As to the
convenience and comfort of the two
methods, different persons are likely to
hold different views."
Mr. Carson then explained an elevat
ed road which Is being constructed in
Germany, where the cars are suspended
from the track Instead of running on
the raila.
"The Boston subway is being built
under some of the most traveled streets
of the city. For most of the distance it
is to have two tracks, but at points
there are four tracks where the cars
can run back without naming to the
end of the line. At the northern termi
nus there is an incline where the cars
i can come to the surface. Stations for
passengers are placed at convenient
distances, usually one In about 1,000
feet.
"The retaining walls of the subway
are of granite and concrete, mostly of
concrete. There are two forms of con
struction employed in the roof, one
made of steel and concrete and the oth
er the brick arch.
"The subway is about twenty-four
feet in width at the Incline, where there
are two tracks, and about sixteen feet
high. In the middle of the subway is a
drain, the side wa!! of which, are of
brick with open Joints, so that thfe wa
ter can eaeily find its way Into It, and
the top is covered over with flags eas
ily removed if the drain needs inspec
tion or repair.
"At the passenger stations there are
two stairways, each fifteen feet In
width. It was not Intended at first to
use elevators at all, but It may be
thought desirable to adopt them at
some stations later on.
'In the work of construction many
pipes were encountered which had to
be removed or passed under. The work
is being so performed as to cause the
least possible hindrance to travel on
the streets. In the daytime one-third
of the street is occupied for the. plant
and material used for the work, and
the other two-thirds Is left for travel.
At night about two-thirds of the street
is occupied in the work.
'Bridges are built over the excava
tions on a level with the street, so that
one passing over them will hardly no
tice the fact. The work Is done by
what is known as the slice method, by
which ten or a dozen sections are being
excavated at the same time, no two be
ing adjoining.
'There are eight fans placed at ap
propriate Intervals to ventilate the tun
nel, each fan being seven feet in diam
eter. It was feared by some that the
excavations would weaken the founda
tions of some of the high buildings, but
the work has so far advanced now that
there is seen to be no danger."
Mr. Carson olosed his lecture with a
rapid description of subways in Buda
pest, Paris, London and Glasgow, and
also a description of the use of the
shield In tunnelling.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83016025/1902-06-28/ed-1/?sp=12&amp;q=boston+subway</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82015415/1898-02-09/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=boston+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>BOSTON'S SUBWAY.
The Boston subway work is nearly
completed. According to present
prospects tliu total cost of the im
provement will fall considerably with-
n the engineer's estimate. 'Jhc total
cost of the subway to date is 4,043,31:1.
The original estimate was $3,000,000.
iV tunnel under the hnrbor to East
lloston is again being discussed, at an
estimated cost of $2,400,000.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87078000/1895-04-16/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=boston+subway</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Boston Subway 1)111 Practically Defeated.
Boston, April' 16. The Boston subway
received a blow In the legislature, whon
tho houso Votod, 98 to' 73, to order to a
third rending tho bill reooallntt tho law
Tolntivo to th6 construction of Subways in
tho city of isoston. The committee on
judiciary has roportod adversely on the
bill to prohibit thp 'use ot' high hats in
theaters.</text>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-early-jazz</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045217/1921-01-22/ed-1/?sp=1&amp;q=Jazz+Saxophone</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Saxophone Wail, Jazz
Make Indians Wild
Again, Says Pastor
Philadelphia, Jan. 21.—Modern
jazz music and dancing are making
the Indians wild again. The roll of
the snare drum and the wail of the
saxophone, combined with the "tod
dle" and the "shimmy" stir atavistic
memories of the tom-tom and the
shriek of the victim at the stake.
So asserted Dr. Henry Beets of
Grand Rapids, Mich., secretary of
missions of the Christian Reformed
church, in an address Friday before
the session of the Friends of the
Indian.
A resolution he introduced seek
ing to forbid Indian youths and girls
from dancing the modern steps, was
adopted and will be sent to the In
dian bureau of the department of
the interior at Washington.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87093354/1921-02-01/ed-1/?sp=10&amp;q=jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Origin of Jazz
(BY MADGE R. CAYTON)
Just what is jazz? One has a vague idea of a dis
orderly number of sounds played entirely for dancing.
But jazz has a far deep.r significance. It is an attempt
to reproduce the marvelous syncopation of the African
Jungle. It is the result of the savage musican's won
derful gift of progressive retarding and acceleration
which is guided by his sense of ewing. He who would
play ja^z nnut have rhythmic aggressiveness. As one
iran put it, ja: z music is the rtelirum tr mens of suyco
pL.i'on. It n strict rhythm without melody.
The words ja;, jazz, jazz, J&3Z, and jascz are of
Afrcan origin but come direct form the Creole patois
and idiom meaning "speed things up." For in th> old
plantation days when the slaves were having one of their
rare holidays an fun would languish, some West Coast
African would say, "jazz hdT up," and then things would
go fast and furious. Today "jazz her up," is still a
slang expression with the same meaning.
There are two types of jazz: One originating in
China, which is called Siames 3 music, and the other
originating in Africa having only a general name of
jazz applied to it. Since the Siamese music or Oriental
jazz, as it is often called, stay:d strictly in China and
underwent no futher development it is not important.
But the jazz that originated in Africa, or the Occidental
jazz is known the world ov-r and because of its impor
tance w> will trace its growth only.
Occidental jazz first came to life on the West Coast
of Africa. There big sturdy warriers danced to tli? music
of throbbing Tom —Toms while the entire jungle was
the accompanying orchestra.
Then it spread, reaching Cuba thru deported slaves.
It found a rich soil there for its growth, since the
jungles of Africa were not so different from the swamps
of Cuba. All of that "Hula Hula stuff," goes straight
back to Africa for its origin. Then jazz was transplanted
into America, entering from the south and creeping
up until it covered all of America. About that time the
war broke out and when our boys went to Europe and
and especially to France they took their beloved jazz
with them. So Paris was initiated into a new world of
music over which they promptly went wild.
But jazz has found her strongest support in the
United States. When jazz arived in America via New
Crleans it almost died leaving only a little spark fostered
by the slaves and New Orleans underworld. For years
jazz has ruled the New Orleans underworld resorts,
thei>- natrons dancing to jazz for gladsome generations
Ragtime and the new dances came from there. Then
slowly, little by little, jazz crept up the Missippi from
resort to resort until it landed in Chicago at Freiburg's
whither it had been proceded by stanzas of "Must I
Hesitate"? "The Blues", 'Frankie and Johnnie," and
other classics of the levee underworld that seems to
please the savage part of us. From there it spread
like wild fire all over the United States, hitting the
Middle West the hardest and the extreme East the
lightest. Jazz has reigned supreme for some years and
CAYTON'S MONTH! V
most likely, will reign for many more for it has invaded
our dance halls, theaters, and concert halls. Even our
churchs have not escaped without their share of tem
petious music. It has even snatched our very song»,
classical and popular, and taken them for its own use
ragging them to death.
One use to think of a band as a group of respectable
looking beings usally with a splendid musical ability.
But when one gazes upon a jazz band he sees a bunch of
s .emingly demented men, contorting themselves and
their instruments far better than a St Vitis dancer.
For the modern jazz band is in reality a young army
artillery. The howitzers of the band ara stationed in
the trap drum, snare drum, cymbals, triangle, wooden
blocks, xylophone, cow bells, rattles and whistles for
the production of various weried noises. The trome
bones represent the field guns, the clarinets, oboes,
saxophones, auto homes and cornets furnish thol rapid
lire batteries. The range being point blank one can
easily s^e why the effect of the drum fire is so complete.
Some say that jazz is sensual. If so why has it
lived in America so long? For this reason: Jazz is of
tho ravage and therefore clemntal in its appeal. It is
bouterous, rough, but the very soul of kindly good
humor and care free merriment. It is the music siren
of the dance for while one is swept thru a neck breaking,
whirl-wind measura his own cares and responsibilities
are brushed aside. In America especially because we,
;00, are of a strenous nature, we nejd and must find
some sort of energetic exercise as a conteractant. The
old fashioned, dreamy waltez and graceful, measured
minuets are things of the past. The tired business man,
the worn out mother, the discouraged poet, as well as
the impatient youths, seek and find relief in jazz. Then
ddi not th dough boys find a wonderful solace in their
beloved jazz? For while under its throes they forgot
the bloody battle field, the stench of decaying bodies;
they even forgot there was such a thing as war. Then
jazz is d mocratic. It is simple enough for any one to
understand and enough of a vampire to coax every one
into a world of oblivion. Can we not then say that jazz
has existed for a purpose and has truly fulfilled that
purpos;.?
But on the other hand one must be careful that the
alluring god of jazz, Mumbo Jumbo, does not lead us so
far from the true god of music, Pan, that we fail to
appr ciate the real classic. Might not one thus uncon
sciouly sell his birth-right for a mess of pottage?
Because jazz is elemental bringing the savage to the
curface, it is dang rous. We cannot afford in our
present stage of civilization to accept the standard of
the savage even if it is only thru the giddy measure of
a dance. True jazz belongs to the "forest primeval"
and is mor: real and refined there than in a hall filled
with dancer.3. The very fact that the growth of jazz
las been thru the under world resorts of America is a
E rong po'nt in i's disfavor. In embrasing what we
now c..11 a necessary evil is there not a chance of jazz
becoming the key to open our souls to the passions our
fore fathers nave spent generations in trying to over
come</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1920-08-15/ed-1/?sp=55&amp;q=danc+Dance+dancing+jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Uri? ?^tE?_Music^s~thTTirsrSten in Dance Reforrii
Jazz Responsible for
Most of the Evils,
Say Teachers
By Wilbur Forrest
JAZZ," that root of much
evil in music, a menace to
established rythmical law
and order and beauty and
grace, is dying its slow but natural
death
Syncopation which tends ^toward
"shimmying," wriggling and hop?
ping about dance floors as in the
days cf prehistoric barbarism is dis?
appearing and, according to those
authorities who make it their busi?
ness to study dancing, the demise of
"jazz" occasions more general joy
than sorrow. Puritanical grand?
mothers and perhaps less prudish
fathers and mothers who attend and
chaperon social dances of the young
need not much longer blush when
their eyes sweep the ballroom. The
youth of the nation may, after all,
grow up amidst less sensuous music
and dancing positions which em?
barrass their elders. A reaction
against this sort of thing is in full
swing in the United States and, like
a burned out plague, "jazz" music
and "jazz" dancing are leaving us.
While "jazz"' still retains its ad?
mirers and supporters, its own
ridiculousness has done more toward
it? eliminatii n than any other agen?
cy, believes Fenton T. Bott, presi?
dent of the American National As?
sociation, Masters of Dancing, who
is now in New York to attend the
thirty- annual convention of
that association, beginning August
25, at the Hotel Astor.
For Clean Dancing
The association, with it? more
than five hundred active members in
every city cf any r-ize in the UYiited
States and Canada, has been one of
the agencies working quietly since
the advent of "jazz" to keep danc?
ing clean and moral. In coopera?
tion with many civic and welfare so?
cieties throughout the country, much
has been done to eliminate the sala
ciou: and immoral features which
this form of syncopation brought
he dance floor.
"We do not recognize the terrr
'jazz,' which is purely a coined
word," Mr. Bot; told The Tribune
"We ever, recognize synco
d.we have nothing agai?.si
of syncopated music.
It can be playi i so brilliantly if
played right, and then again it can
ther form so sensu?
ous and evil that it harks clear back
to the wild and irresponsible barba?
rism of the dark ages. We have
tried and preach modera?
tion. Civilization has begun to re?
volt against the wrong kind of syn?
copation, tins so-called 'jazz,' whicr
during tne more unrestrained perioc
of the war swept the country witl
a crop of immodesty in both son?
and dance in its wake. It first ap
peared on the stage, and eventually
it audaciously entered the publi;
dance hail and private ballroon
alike.
"There is a decided upward tren?
in music now, as compared with i
year ago," continued the dance mas
ter president. "New York, a leade
in entertainment whose example i
followed everywhere, is setting
cleaner pace. Compare New York'
roof gardens of some of the leadin?
hotels, compare the theaters, th
moving picture palaces and even th
dance halls now with a year age
Twelve months ago the 'jazz' crnz
was everywhere. It was reflecte^
from the stage, the dance floor anc
in a wave of ribald, suggestive song
Written and distributed to every cot
ner of the land. It invaded th
home in the form of magazine il
lustrations, on lithographed cover
of sheet music, in graphophone an
pianola records.
Displaced hy Good Musie
"To-day we find 'jazz' dying
natural death. This form of syncc
Pation is giving way in motion pi<
tore houses to pipe organs and grea
orchestras playing real and beaut
f'Jl music, it is to be heard less i
a11 the theaters. The r?of garde
dancing inclosures are reflecting let
and less the ridiculous movements c
oncers inspired by slow, barbaror
?Ksic Public dance halls are fa
?leaner, if we are to believe the at
%rities. And all of this is n(
toly true of New York but of th
country at large."
The president of the America
National Association, Masters
Dancing, ?3 a citizen of Daytoi
Ohio, where he conducts a dancin
Waden-y attended by juvenile men
oers of some of Dayton'a first fam
including "Young Jimmy" Co:
a?ed fourteen, son of the Democrat
nominee for President.
"It is such folks as these that ov
association seeks to protect in i
campaign for cleaner dancing ar
ottner music," he said. "We do n
concern ourselves with the ty]
JJwch demanda vulgarity and lice
Jiousness. They are not of our pro
But, as an organization, v
*?st a stand against that so
J- thing if we aro to hold up 01
'?ttds/*
There has been virtually no op?
position to the anti-jazz campaign
waged by his organization except
from a few unscrupulous dance hall
proprietors, said the president.
"Dancing is an essential," he
added. "What would tens of thou?
sands of people do nightly in New
York if they were not permitted to
go somewhere, meet socially, and
dance? If the places where these
people meet are decent there can be
no finer, more healthful or enjoy?
able recreation anywhere."
"What do you consider good or
bad positions in dancing?" he was
asked.
"It is difficult to illustrate posi?
tions," he answered. "Anyone can
see with a glance over the dance
floor wdiether positions are good or
bad. When you take hold of a girl
to dance, common sense and decency
should prompt your position. If your
attitude toward her is proper, you
will not crush your body against
hers nor place your cheek against
hers.
A Form of Exercise
"Clean dancing is an efficient
form of exercise, amusement and
recreation for both sexes. It devel?
ops muscle coordination which re?
sults in grace of movement. Girls
run, roll hoops and skip the rope
during their more youthful years
but later their play becomes more
sedentary, and should be supple?
mented by class exercises and
games. Dancing is one of these.
Dancing is likewise a mind quicken
er. By fixing the attention, bringing
to bear the force of will on the com?
plicated actions of the body, it edu?
cates the mental faculties. This is
especially true of aesthetic dancing,
during the performance of which
the muscles of the arms and trunk
are used, as well as those of the
legs.
"Sometimes the dancing school is
misunderstood," continued the mas?
ter. "The dishonest and unscrupu?
lous dance hall proprietor may give
the clean dancing academy a bad
name, just as some classes of thea?
ters may give the theater a bad
name. The theater is a great insti?
tution, but it is all wrong from the
wrong standpoint. The same is true
of dancing and dancing schools. The
wrong angle may be applied to them
just as to the theater.
To Ask Church's Aid
The American National Associa?
tion during its coming convention in
New York will renew a long-studied
effort to gain the cooperation of the
Methodist Church in the promotion
of clean dancing. This denomina?
tion takes a stand in its "blue laws"
against dancing in any form, and
during the last General Conference,
some years ago, a resolution to
amend the "blue laws" was voted
down. A group of "progressive"
Methodists, led by J. Henry Smythe,
of New York, is to-day avowedly in
favor of dancing, and will carry the
fight into the next Methodist General
Conference. The "conservatives"
are said to be adamant in their re?
fusal to lift a ban prescribed almost
half a century ago on many forms of
amusement.
"Dancing is older than Christi?
anity," said the president of the
dancing masters. "It will live so
long as there is music. It is our
struggle to keep this form of amuse?
ment clean and moral, and we feel
that the Methodist Church can do
more for humanity by helping us
than by opposing dancing in general.
It is only the older and more con?
servative Methodists who now op?
pose dancing. Younger Methodists
favor it."
Allied with the dancing masters'
organization against what is termed
improper music and dancing, many
social and civic societies have
been doing their part. A pamphlet
issued by the organization, contain?
ing "Rules, Regulations and Sugges?
tions Governing S^pcial Dancing,"
j has been distributed by the thousand
^y social welfare societies and the
H-elfare department of the United
States government. Universities
and colleges, demanding authorita?
tive knowledge on proper and im?
proper dancing during school func?
tions, have beer, supplied with these
rules and regulations almost every
where in the United States.
The Actors' Eejuity Association,
?m organization composed of thou?
sands of actors and actresses, is an
able element allied against forms of
music and dancing which might tend
toward a bad effect on the general
public.
The dancing masters have success?
fully solicited the cooperation of
"^ong publishers, who have in turr?
i toned down suggestive titles and
Mthographs on sheet music. Phonr?
graph companies, spending tens o?
thousands of dollars monthly in
j brightly colored magazines, have
been prevailed upon to make their
advertising less "jazzy."
The General Federation of Worn
j en's Clubs, one of the most active
agencies in the United States, is
working for music reform. At the
biennial conference in June at D.es
Moines a resolution was passed con?
demning popular songs which smack
of vulgarity and initiating an open
campaign for better American music.
Mrs. Marx E. Oberndorf er (Anne
Shaw Faulkner), cf Chicago, wife
of the famous pianist, selected na
tional music chairman, is to-day
planning and directing the music
activities of more than 19,000 wom?
an's clubs. By means of music mem
ory contests in schools, churches, de?
partment stores, industries and in?
stitutions and the establishment of
i community music centers, she plans
to save a nation threatened by
"jazz" and "ragtime."
i The Federated Catholic Societies
of the United States'recently recog?
nized and indorsed the "anti-jazz'
movement, and through the federa?
tion magazine invited the attentior
of all Catholic schools and societie;
io the virtues of such a movement
Society's Aid I? Asked
In a quiet way appeals have gone
forth to society girls and women tc
i set the example in dancing for theii
less moneyed and perhaps less fortu
nate sister?the working giri?wh<
is prone to copy their methods.
"There are many rules to goven
?lancing, the American dancing maa
i ters explain in their pamphlet o
regulations. Here are some of them
"Dance music should be brigh
I and cheerful, properly accented am
the phrases well divided.
"Cheap, vulgar music of the ex
treme 'jazz' type invites cheap, vul
gar, meaningless dancing.
"It is needless to expect refinei
dancing when the music lacks all re
finement, for, after all, what is danc
ing but an interpretation of music?
There are ten plain "don'ts" fo
the proper dancing function.
"Don't permit 'jazz' music to b
j played. Such music almost force
dancers to use jerky half steps an
invites immoral variations.
"Don't permit young men to hoi
their partners tightly. Ofttimes thi
is the fault of the gentleman's part
ner. Both dancers should assume
light, graceful position.
"Don't permit partners to danc
with cheeks close or touching. Whe
dancers put their cheeks together
is simply a case of public love mai
ing.
The "N?eck Hold" Barred
"Don't permit meek holds.* TI
gentleman's arm should encircle h
partner's waist, his hand restin
lightly at her spine, just above tl
waistline, and the lady's left an
should not encircle the gentleman
shoulders or neck.
"So-called 'shimmy' dancing is
shaking or jerking of the upp<
body while taking short steps
standing still and should not 1
tolerated. Short ?idesteps, fir
PENTON T. BOTT, president of the American National
Association Masters of Dancing, which in its convention
here next week will begin a fight on jazz music and dancing.
The dancing positions shown are those approved by the Na?
tional Association.
I right, then left, when done continu?
ously, are not conducive to refined
dancing and should not be permitted.
"Don't permit elancers to take j
i either exceptionally long or short
steps. The proper dancing step
should be the same as a natural
walking one, except in exhibition
dancing, which belongs to the stage i
and not the ballroom.
"Don't dance from the waist up;
I dance from the waist down.
"Don't permit suggestive move
ments.
"Don't permit dancers to copy the
extremes that are now used on the
modern stage.
"For the benefit of refined people
don't hesitate to request objection?
able dancing couples to leave the
room. Remember that the majority
of the people want to dance cleanly."
"True refinement should be evi?
dent in every act of life," says the
book of regulations, "and this is
especially noticeable in a gentle
f
America Is Already
Turning Against
Vulgar Dances

man's attitude toward his partner
while dancing. Good t=ct* demands
that a gentleman stand a reasonable
distance from his partner, and that
he show due consideration in lead?
ing her through the different sleps.
Thoughtlessness on the part of both
lady and gentleman in taking out?
landish positions is responsible for
most of the criticism directed
:.gainst modern social dancing.
"All exaggerated movements, espe?
cially of the upper part of the body,
are in very bad taste in social danc?
ing and are never found with true
refinement and culture. Couples
dancing with their faces together
show such extreme* bad taste that
it should be unnecessary even to call
attention to it."
"All in all," says President Fenton
Botts, "the campaign has done much
to cleanse modern dancing, but
'jazz,' the root if it all, has done
more to eliminate itself than all the
campaigns.
"The American 'jazz' craze has
been like a popular celebration?for
a day or two all is enthusiasm, flags
and speeches. Soon it wanes and
dies its natural death."
Jazz, he believes, is now dying
that natural e'.eath, and European
nations which so quickly adopted the
American craze will see its Ameri?
can demise spread across the seas.
Jazz has had its day.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88076526/1922-01-25/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=dance+dancing+jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>JAZZ HOME LIFE
REV. CASE DEPICTS 'HOME LIFE*
IN BABYLON, CHICAGO
AND DEV. LAKE.
Ask the historian and he will tell' and serve it so mildly that all the
you that jazz is characteristic sign- te.ng may be lost. So remember that
board that indicates that the road ends it's all coated with frost—as com
soon and unless a turn to the right is pared with the real thing. It ."hall
taken the .nation or civilization travel. |be as gentle as expurgation, fumiga
ling along that road will soon be hurt- I tion and typewritten formaldehyde
ling over the precipice into oblivion, can make it. And yet, I warn you
Such the case with Babylon, Assyria, if you have a weak heart, if you faint
Egypt, Persia, Greece, Rome. In each easily, or if you feel when you see
case orgies of sensuous, lewd dancing a pretty blondined actress wearing
preceeded the downfall of these na- a peek-a-boo waist, stop at this line!
tions. Early in their history they Don't read farther at the peril of .your
were strong and clean of life. Then conscience and good health, because
came- the time when they were un- I mean to attempt to tell briefly the
clean, enervated by luxury, sapped by story of Pierre Louys, "Aphrodite
dissipation, and overcome by excess! Dr. Straton, the great New
-and weakened by licentiousness and York preacher speaking of the same
then in those latter days that were! spectacle says:
characterized by a prevelence of what "Nothing was left to the imagina
we would call today "jazz" they: tion. Every appeal was to the sen
danced themselves into the abyss. suos and the fleshly. .It was a night-
Let us ask the scienest what he mare of nude men and women, with
thinks -about this. bare legged negro men, in addition to,
"I do. not known about the loss .white men, squirming in and out and
of souls" says a biologist, "at least rubbing against the practically naked
in a- metaphyseal sense. What pen-1 white girls. It was an orgy of sen
alties may be incurred in the here- suality and shame, with men and wo
after by sinful or improper conduct men, in a condition of almost complete
on earth- are- beyond the ken of ex- undress, hugging each other, and slob.
bering over each other and rolling on
couches with each other, and danc
ing in feignod drunken revelry to
gether."
perimental science. But I do know
that natural law cannot be violated
with* impunity either for ourselves
or for the next generation. Hell
to mois a retrogression of the species.
In this sense I agree with any theo
logian as'• to the consequences of
degrading practices. There is no use
to quibble over details In so far
as jazz dancing relaxes morality and
undefatiines the institution of the fami
ly it is an- element of tremendous evil.
Besides the testimony of the scitfn
tist I woul 1 place the words of Prof.
J. Louis Guyon who characterizes
the "shimmey" as a "pelvic massage"
and who'' declares' that many couples
should' have marriage licences before
stepping upon the dance floor. Prof.
Guyon, by the way is the proprietor
of the largest dance hall on the west
side Of Chicago. It is significent that
he has barred jazz dancing and even
the "fox trot" He says:
"Ndw modern dancing is creating
an army of degenerates: It is break
ing down the moral resistance of the
younger generation and taking its
toll :in girls who succumb, under its
insidious influence, dancing the auto
mobile rides and "parties" that follow
the evenings dance. I am not a re
former, but I aiji against the "one
stepif andv any other vis-a-vis step.
Present conditions cannot go on. If
the publicdoes not become nauseated
with its ow.n ball-room conduct and
reform of its own accord, dancing
will have to be purified by statute:"
(from an interview in Chicago Tri- T'°r you HOLY and you are not doing
bune.) it.
The scientist is interested solely in "Peace, peace, there is no peace"
the physical and mental aspect but
he condemns because he knows that
70 per cent of the special surgical
operations upon women, are duedir-
ectl£ or indirectly to the disobedience
of these laws of God and Nature? He
alsff knows that 60 per cent of the
blintl are deprived the light of day
with. of lashed nerves that is behind
With the jazz dance and for it we
I -do*" not- believe a bridgroom or
biidc ever lived who did not register
AW. WHAT'S THE USE
HOPS ON CROWDED
0 TCOLLEN CAR-
^ome picture: That sew.. to be
the popular verdict on Rev. P. H.
Case's sermon Sunday n'ght relating
to drinking,. dancing and dissipation,
which constituted a large part of
the society doings of Babylon and
Borne, and more recently of Chicago
—and" Devils Lake. We are using
only a part of the sermon, and so we
leave the reader to the tender mercies
of the preacher:
"The other evening I called upon high and holy resolves when they, next generation but that perhaps
you to 'take stock' and presented heard "The Wedding March" Or our childrens children will come back
some of the facts to you. Let us Promise Me at their wedding. In the to sanity of life. He is right but for
face them this evening. What doj spiritual realm, too, music plays its one thing. That is the power of
they mean I am sure that anyone part and many a mar. has found his God. If we stop, think and then
that is fainninded will have to ad-j way to the Cross made clearer and (REPENT and turn to HIM he can
mit that the life today is tending easier by the sweet singing of God's and will cleanse us. There is a great
hellward, and our pace in that dir- Music. So many young souls tonight I revival needed today. It is needed
ection is swift. We are having a' are having seared upon the retina of among the poor and needy and among
"good time" as we go. All kinds their memories the picture of lost the outcasts of our cities and waste
of exhilaration and "joy rides" and virtue and stolen honor and the music places but I believe that even more
"jazz." We have jazz music, and jazz that accompanies that picture is this
pictures, and jazz married life. We demnable unspeakable jazz.
have turned on the gas, in fact have! Referring to jazz moving pictures,
clamped the accelerator down and as Mr. Case said the pictures he had seen
one man said in speaking of a recent here had been clean, with a few ex
"party" more truely than perhaps he ceptions. He quoted from Archie Bell
knew or meant: "We are having a dramatic critic of the Cleveland Sun
hell of a time" That is just it. I day-News Leader who said in review
er I do not ask you to take my! ing a certain play:
word for this. "{'11 put it in an ice shaker, cool it
/U/Y///A'
Why do I bring this in. Because
it is typical of the "jazz picture" of
today. They say it is art. It is the
Devil's art. Just the same art that
he used centuries ago in that "Grove
of Aphrodite" which is dep-cted in
that play and which ruin ad one cf thj
greatest civilizations the world has
ever known.
GRA55 TOR.
SV'NG'NC STRAP
is it needed among the rich and those
who should be cultured. Those are
the hardest, too, reach. But if it
does not come WE ARE LOST. As
Lloyd George says: "It is Christ or
Chaos" I am praying with all my heart
I hat it may be Christ.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058393/1922-06-18/ed-1/?sp=34&amp;q=dance+dances+dancing+jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A French cartoonist's very sarcastic com on the absurd lengths to which he thinks the Americans have carried thir acrobatic dances. The v
picture show the artist's conception of (1), the Jugglers' Jazz; (2), the Upside-Down Camel Walk; (3) the Back-to-Back Trot; (4), the gxaa
Marine Glide; (5), the Tipsy-Topsy Toddle; and (6), the Lunch Counter Whirl. jJuSSti The Apache dance, a Parisian invention which gj
BEj the rest of the world a severe shock, but wM
Leaders of French Thought Denounce Our Syncopated ;jBK
Melodies and the Steps That Keep Time with 1
I f I i HAT Paris is a gay and wicked
I I city is on of the fixed ideas we
Americans from youth collect and
H cling to. The very name of France's
B capital suggests a high old time. We are
B in the habit of announcing a forthcom-
B ing visit to Paris with a wink and a
H devilish expression, and our friends all
I tell us to be good, and if we cafci't be
B good to be careful.
I PariB to us is the place whero the blue
laws (Base from troubling. It is the
1 merry city where the lid is not only off,
1 bat is lost. There, it is the American no-
I tion,tho writers of naughty French farces
1 get a profusion of plots from
jj real life. r-
m Paris, where life sparkles i
B like champagne 1 Paris, where L
you can get champagne! Our Br JmW
9 prohibition law has given that BBwBb
Eft city just so much more of a WmWm9
M reputation for joviality.
We expect extremes in dress, K3Ku9
g dancing and so forth from HKe3
ft Paris. And from Paris and
things Parisian we look for flB&Bgg
M our best supply of shocks, HHH
jffi startlers and causes for gasps. uSBt wfajft
5 And now Paris hm turned "gS Wffia
am around and got horribly
B shocked at us! It's such an ,IB
B amazing, topsy-turvy state of H y
B affairs as we never could havo J i
B imagined. r.
B That which the people of L
6 Paris have taken occasion to
H get shocked at is our jazz
m dances.
B While the business of Paris aWii
B being shocked by anything
B American may seem funny to Americ
ft us, to the Parisians it is no
ft laughing matter. Paris, nay, all France,
ft is taking the whole matter with as
tounding seriousness. Press, pulpit and
powerful public leaders all are thun
j dering against the dance importations
from America. And they are accusing
them of being responsible for more aw
ful things than you can shake we al
most said shake a shimmy a stick at
Those making the charges against our
jazz steps run all the way from national
figures, writers, doctors and philosophers
to a famous nude dancer, who has come
right out and declared that the prances,
j wiggles and slides from the U. S. A. are
the limit and then some.
France certainly is much upset. She
Is up in arms as she has not been on any
non-political question for some time. The
French dancing masters are bewailing
the damage to their art. French musi
cians are protesting the assaults on their
music. French parents are worried about
(their children.
And we? Well, over here in America
we can hardly understand it. We were
not surprised when jazz dancing was the
target for a good deal of fire within
our own lines. That was to be expect
ed. But what is to happen when Paris
accuses us of the rough stuff? Wasn't
it from Paris that those Apache dances
came? Those knock-down and drag-out
steps from the Parisian underworld, with
their wild abandon and unleashed pas
sion? Beside that, we had thought that
any of the little measures we tread
seemed like mere minuets.
But the French, it appears, think dif
ferently on that subject.
The "Revue Mondiale," influential
Paris paper, has got together a mass
of opinions on American dance steps
which is not at all flattering. In fact,
some of them might be called damning
and others of them shouldn't really be
printed.
Regina Badct, who appears on the
stage and dances in a string or so of
beads and a few bracelets, goes on rec
ord as saying that the American stylo
of dancing is to be condemned for its
sensuousness.
Modern dancing is low and ugly, Abel
Hermant says. Victor Marguerite terms
it "a precocious and dangerous de
floration." B. Baudrillart. of the Acad
emy, admits that reaction from the
war is some excuse, but is much worried
at the effect of the craze for dancing at
all hours. One correspondent branded
dancing as "a hypocritical form of ob
taining Illicit pleasure Medical ver-
Their Blare As "Ugly, Ridiculous and Mra' 1
Indecent," but the Public Refuses M I
To Be Shocked
an jazz has so captivated all France th
diets handed down by mental specialists,
surgeons, nerve specialists and others
condemn the dancing of to-day as very
bad for the moral welfare, as well as
for the future of the race.
"And it comes from America," they
end up by saying, accusingly.
"Look at that new dance, the 'Balan
cello,' that came from Genoa around the
time of the conference, and was about
the only thing that happened then," the
French cry. "It's a one-step and a
shiver combined. Terrible! Even though
the Americans wouldn't come to Genoa,
we are willing to wager they sent that
dance."
There's no telling where the craze will
end, if you believe the French papers
At the head of this page is
reproduced a famous French
artist's very sarcastic com- .gg
ment on the absurd lengths to &0&
which he thinks the Amcri-
cans have carried their acro
batic dances. He pictures six dances
which, if not already in vogue, he be
lieves soon will be.
No. 1 is what he calls the Jugglers'
Jazz. It is a trifle wearing on the back
of the neck, but it does leave the feet
so free.
Then there is the Upside-Down Camel
Walk, in which the couple is shown in
the act of reversing.
No. 8 is the Back-to-Back Fox Trot.
Even more criticism than was aroused
by the cheek-to-cheek dancing may bo
occasioned by this back-to-back stuff.
Next comes the Marine Glide, a step
which it will not be wise to indulge in
for at least one hour after eating.
No. 5 is the Tipsy-TojiBy Toddle, a
combination of the shimmy, the Chicago
and the giant swing.
The last is a novelty which the artist
christens the Lunch Counter Whirl.
But the French are not all taking the
American manner of tripping it on the
light fantastic toe in such a light fan
tastic mood. Some are treating it in
what they consider a spirit of stark,
grim realism. There's Paul Bourget, of
the French Academy, for instance, who
has announced that his next novel is to
deal with the adventures of a young girl,
who, smitten by the microbe of the
dance, is dragged down and down as if
by drink.- "Dope" and the gigolos, or.
professional dancing men, then compass
her ruin.
Abel Hemant hesitates to subject
the characters in his novels to the
tango, maxixc and fox trot. "These so-
ville loses its attraction -7
when the intoxicating BmBP J
music strikes up and IH I jjP
trotting on the sandy :r 0L J$S- 'j
beach as shown 8HHr V
in the recent ijp i j
y...7,r
BHkP costume Regina Badet, fa- j&jfiS
-this mow for the Jljf f
called American W)&$$& -Sira
dances," he said, K''-'- B
"are ugly, ridic- Wfe;
ulous and inde- v.
cent, and I can
no t understand
how any mother y.,
can watch her
daughters danc
ing them without Bh i
blushing to the i
roots of her hair X'-' 1 r
"There are a B?-"-'", ,y J
t h w :-.:nd .!eu;r.M- of f '!Kt
love," he declared, add- Wmjffii
ing that dances are
based on love, "and
dancers should choose B
the noblest, instead of jastf
the most impure. Every
gesture must be a sym- sSn
bpl, and the state of WS
the nation's civilization arc
may be determined bv the f;
fact that the gestures do not mm
approach too closely to the JPp '5
reality of the thing symbol- 1
ized."
A number of French scien
tists and savants whose words carry
weight all have uttered words of cau
tion against the harm to the moral wel
fare of the nation which may result
from the physical excitement engendered
by the styles of modern dancing. Mme.
Augustin Lofert, whose husband direct
ed the French Academy of the Dance,
deplores cheek-to-cheek dancing, hug
ging and wrestling holds. Maurice Level
sees peril in the habit of women in leav
ing off their cornets for a dance.
v M
M; raris
Jm thinks
IJH far less
demoralizing than the
American jazz dances
f oust jazz and
'-r the dances it
inspires has been im
y puted to as high a per-
sonage in France as
Premier Poincare, who is said to
haye been prompted to the under
taking by the municipal council.
Among those complaining have been the
French musicians who have been losing
employment because of the prevalence
of the darkey jazz bands. The banjo
and the saxophone have superseded the
violin and the flute, Only negroes are
considered to be the proper performers
on jazz instruments, and restaurants and
dance halls will employ only them. It
is called the "Black Peril."
Yet in spite of this general condem
nation of the American jazz dances,
thoir hold on the French public grows
stronger and stronger.
Dance places are springing up like
mushrooms and their number never
seems to decrease. Maurice and Hughes
have opened a new palace on the Rue
Cammartin. The "So Different" and the
floors at the Carlton, the Claridgc, the
Scheherazade, Mirabeau and Ba1 Bul
lier all are crowded.
It has come to be pretty well under
stood in Paris that if you do not shake
a mean foot, you had better learn, for
a wallflower has a better time Staying
at home and knitliner.
A new dancing place is said to open
every week, and even at that the
after-theater crowds have difficulty in
finding dancing space and that in
spite of the fact that modern dancing
takes so little space.
There are attempt? to introduce
l ew steps, but all of them are vain
unless they bring new innovations in
American jazz. And those seem to be
forthcoming from time to time, al
though American reformers are rav
ing and legislators uselessly intro
duce bills that attempt to prescribe
the holds to be used in our
dancing and the distance to
be kept.
The American brand of
jazz dancing continues to be 9
potent enough to cause great ..va
alarm in France and to re
verse the general order of
things, so that the people of :;W A
Paris actually are shocked vff 8
at us. 1 fel
It has been suggest- if ffiWB
ed, however, that there JmHbm
may be some jealousy Ji flKjuH
m it all, and that there 'f Jnfefljgg
are Frenchmen whore- Jf kOBBm
Bent anything so live- Jmkb
ly as our jazz !gr
dances being
French chain- 'tW
pagne. f -J
But the p.. (T
French should .4
remember that
the all-con- "f f
qucring reign
of jazz be- -Jit&
gan some time before the period of
-'routh.
condemns jazz v 'f K
jHBFt :B</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn78001466/1921-09-19/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=dancing+jazz+Jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Jazz Origin Is a
Mystery; Composers
Refuse to Claim It
Jv Y,-ei. S?- 11 U is almost
impossiK 5 ffiii :t who is to blame
for jsja Jx3K.3c.
Kay. a question which
maay ocaaijfr Vt no means inedn
snun'.al A; f.rst thought, one,
flight p:x ti rrsronsibility on the
danein txju-'Jwrs, but if you ask
them, thy vhrug their tuexdoed
shoulilrs in a rhythmic manner and
plead not guilty. Its the fault of the
composers, they will tell you, pass
ing the buck in double-quick ttnie.
The denial o ithe composers is
sharp, their contradiction flat and
the explanation of the why o fjazz
music natural they give the public
what it wants.
emingly the public is divided
in its opinion on this big question.
Some say the younger generation is
to blame.' Jazz dancing and jazz
music are, to repeat their own words
just exactly what one might expect
when the youth of land gads about
in sporty automobiles, simulates con
tempt for Mrs. Grundy's ideas and
shows a determination to do every
thing in a fast and snappy way.
Others maintain that jazz is a nat
ural reaction to Victorian customs.
A few of their neighbors, almost
abandoning hope, resign themselves
to the thought that that something
called the spirit of the age is really
Getting Your Fruit To Market
1
TO HOYS FLORIDA'S 1920-21
CROP ALOHE REQUIRED-
600 Million Pounds of Ice.
Costing $1,700,000
in 25,71 Refrigerator
Carloads
TP
y V fo, fit
the reason for fitful dancing styles,
expressing wonder- the while as to
just what this little old world is
coming to.
The manner in which the dancing
instructors put the blame on the
chaps who create tunes is exemplified
by R. W. Vizay, president of the Am
erican Society of Dancing Teachers.
"Dancing is wholly a matter of
music," he said. "The reason a
waltz is out of date is because there
is no' Strauss today to compose a real
one and make the people glide to it
When good music is composed, good
dancing will result. As long as you
have jazz mtTSfc you will have jazz
dancing."
A very small proportion of couples
dance properly these days, Mr. Viz
ay remarked. Take the ordinary
ballroom, he said, and you will see 20
couples toddling, five shimmying,
three doing the "Chicago" and ten
dancing properly. The teachers show
their pupils how to dance properly,
he continued, but when they leave
and begin reacting to the jazz tunes
of the cabaret and the roof garden
well, now, how are you going to keep
'em from shaking a mean ankle?</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045774/1921-03-13/ed-1/?sp=82&amp;q=immoral+jazz</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038531/1919-09-03/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=Immoral+Jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Local Terpsichorean
  Immoral Dances; Jazz Craze Must Go
Appeal Made to Musicians to
Chaperones Included in Warning.
Th danolng that ha been Indulged
In at some of the public dancing hall
In Chattanooga haa been the subject
of much comment lately. Orchestra
leader are beginning to think that
unless they feature that "Jazs Blues"
they will not be popular. The young
girl who attend these dance, ac
cording to those who are best In
formed are beginning to feel the same
way. In other word, the danolng
publlo ha gone "Jazx mad."
The first step to take In order to
reform the publlo dancing hall," ac
cording to Al Wilson, of the Wilson
Dancing achool, "1 to have strict
rule in these publlo places, and to
have some one there to see that they
are enforced." Mr. Wilson states
that while the average person dances
for the love of dancing, on the other
hand there are some who dance only
for the opportunity of coming In
close contact with those of the op
posite sex. For thin reason, Mr. Wll
on ayi, the hugging and cheek-to-cheek
dancing must go. He says
that the time ha come when the
people must take a stand against all
!:lnd of (Immoral dancing. He
print out that the lover of dancing
do not necessarily have to go back
to th ancient dancing, for the mod
ern dances, If danced properly, are far
more attractive and graceful. He
state that even "the )nzz" fox trot
with the tickle-toe can be danced In
a moral way. But unfortunately the
average young couple, he adds, danc
ing the fox trot, very closely resemble
Jclly-ln-a-bowl on a frosty morning.
The dancing- master continued "Some
of our best girls dance this way be
cause they think It la 'stylish.' They
mean absolutely no harm, but think
to be popular they must rub all the
skin oft the left side of their face
against the wiry beard of some young
man. How some people can dance
all hugged up I past me; fact Is,
they don't dance, they Just hop.
Notice a couple of real dancer on
exhibition, and you will see at least
four Inches of space between them.
That Is the real comfortable way to
dance. You must be educated In
proper dancing." x
Warming to hi subject, Mr. Wil
son says: "We appeal to mothers
and chaperones to help us elevate
dancing. We also appeal to musi
cians. They do not realize how much
help they can be. The way Is to cut
out so much "Jazz" and play the
muslo more like It Is written.
"Don't think that you must go back
fifty years ago and pick up the dances i
"AH! YES, COST OF LOVING HER
CERTAINLY HAS GONE UP!"
(BY N. P.
(BY N. P. BABCOCK.)
"Why don't you write a piece,"
(young men of hi sort never ay
artlclle), "on the high cost of living?"
asked a youth of my acquaintance
the other day,
"Just what do you mean?" I asked.
"Well," he replied, "from what pop
say (he always refers to his father
as though the latter were only a bot
tle of ginger beer), "it must cost a
fellow about four times as much to
be mushy on a girl now as It did In
your day."
"Mushy?" I repeated. In as dignified
voice a I could command.
"Oh, well, to be 'keeping company'
with her; that's what pop calls it. To
be her 'steady, you know, with a
lew to getting spliced up some day.
Pop say it didn't cost him as much
in a month as I spend in a week. It's
something fierce today, take It from
me!"
"Under such condition I have no
desire to 'take It from you,'" I re
plied, "but why has the cost advanced
so much? Doe the modern girl re
iulre more candy than her mother
or grandmother did?"
"Candy?" I wish you could have
heard the acorn In hi voice. "That's
what my father asked me how much
I spent for candy. As If that cut any
ice. He says he used to take a box to
mother every Saturday evening and
It was never all gone when he called
again on Sunday night. 'Calling' on a
girl; that seems to have been the
old style. Spending the whole eve
nlpg cither In the parlor or out on
the front steps. 'And what did the
rest of the bunch do?' I aaked pop.
'What bunch?' asked he. 'Why, the
bunch mother traveled with,' said I.
'There wasn't any bunch,' he an
swered. Now, Just think of that! No
wonder a fellow could get married
early."
"And does your your I
hazarded the word, 'Inamorata' be
long to a bunch?"
"You said it," he replied. "She be
longs to two; the downtown bunch
where she works and the uptown
bunch where she lives.
"She's a stenographer, and a peach
ot a one, at that," he continued, "and
she's got a mother who Is so stuck
on the movies that she'll sit through
two shows of the same film while the
rest of us are over at the soda pal
ace, but I always have to trot out and
get a pint of ice cream ror her when
Askbur Grocer!
There has been
no raise in the
price of Postum
as there has
been in Coffee
From every-stand
pointpocketbook
health taste
It pays to use-
72iere& a
THE CHATTANOOGA NEWS;- CHATTANOOGA, TENN., WEDNESDAY,
Joins Fight on
Leave Out Some of "the Rag.'
that your grandparent left off. In
fact we don't have to go back a day,
But go ahead, for the "Jar wiggle" is
becoming a thing of the past. The
"CUT THE RAG"
Al Wilson and Hi Wife Advocate
4-inch Space Between Partner
if Dance Is to Be Artistio.
people are demanding straight,
smooth dancing, and they are going
to have it. Six months ago we pre
dicted that the dancing teachers' as
sociation would wage war on "Jazz,"
and our prediictlon has come true.
We feel that we are giving the dance
Ing public a warning1 of what Is to
come If the social reformer and the
preacher once start a war on danc
ing. For as things exist now, they
will certainly find good support.
"We hope the dancers will take
warning and not let the reformers
find one chance to complain when
they start. The good people can set
the example and others can be forced
to follow."</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045774/1922-10-15/ed-1/?sp=121&amp;q=immoral+jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A Defens
Continued from Preceding Page.
the waiter came and fanned me with the
check. Then I passed out.
When I came to I married Jessica and
paid the check with her dowry.
Was that immoral?
Yet they say jazz is ruining the morals
?f our youth. In my thesis, which I shall
submit to the Fellows of the Harvard and
"V" 'i In pnrnni'i i inno ort/I m??la nf t
Bryn Mawr and Vassar corporations, 1
shall convince the world that jazz is justified,
inevitable and harmless. I shall pepper
the thesis with enough allusions in Latin
to get it by as a thesis.
My argument will be along the fol^wing
lines, and see if you don't think there is
some sense to it: These are parlous times.
They are the times in which every good
1
If this was a slow age tl
man should come to the aid of his country.
Life is not the placid thing it was when
women wore crinolines. Life could not be
anything but placid with a crinoline
around.
(You understand this is all in outline,
sort of.)
The same thing applies to any of those
getups the girls of ancient times used to
rig themselves out in, for what reason I
the stars alone know. Those twelfth cen- j
tury effects with the stovepipe hats and
nine or ten yards of gauze floating off
them for no reason whatsoever. I refer to
the headgear of the Sleeping Beauty period.
Small wonder she went to sleep!
And those Elizabethan ruffs. No wonder
history states that Queen Elizabeth was
straight laced. How could Sir Waiter
Raleigh put his arm around her neck when
it was alreadv done ud in enough ma
terial to keep the Troy collar factories
going a month?
I shall go on to point out that modern
life is essentially rapid and therefore essentially
jazzy. I shall prove by actual
statistics and charts that the slowest man
in the United States to-day is seven and
one-quarter times faster than the fastest
man was when it took nine days to get
from Boston to Philadelphia.
And what is more, 1 guarantee to do
this wunout masing a single jose aooui
Philadelphia! Or Boston!
The music of a period is a reflection
of the mood of the time. If a people feeli
jazzy they have jazz music and they live
jazz lives, and the refined, moral peoplQ
who are fortunately always in the minority,
may denounce until they denounce
themselves hoarse, but it will not do them
any good. If a people feels minuettish; if
circumstances are of a minuettish type,
then you will find slow, stately music such
as our ancestors of Colonial times had,
when the fastest thing out was Paul Re- j
vere.
We have the Twentieth Century Lim- I
ited, Conan Doyle, airplane mails, Ford
NEW YORK HERALD,
e of Jazz
tractors, trans-oceanic non-stop flights,
monkey glands, radio concerts, votes for
women, subways and a 75:25 standard of
morals.
I admit that we would be better off
without the radio concerts.
Nevertheless, under these circumstances,
who is going to dance the minuet today?
Anyone suggesting such a thing
would be and should be laughed to scorn.
Jessica would not even dance a gavotte.
and everyone knows there is an element
of risk, of thrill in the gavotte. Your
correspondent has seen men and women,
cold sober, trip themselves or each other
during a gavotte movement, and serious
injury has ensued.
If things ever slow down, and they
never will, then jazz will go. but it never
hey'd be dancing minuets.
will. It is here to stay until we revert
to type. That is why your correspondent
feels sure that you would get a good
laugh out of these clippings about jazz,
wherein almost all of the dominies, lots
of the dancing masters, and even Victor
Herbert, attempt to take falls out of
jazz. Their protests are futile and, incidentally,
they arc all wrong because as
Whatchacallit has 60 aptly said: "Whatever
is, is right," and jazz certainly is,
isn't it?
Your correspondent has proved his case
for jazz, and he hasn't even said a word
about the war!</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026749/1920-09-07/ed-1/?sp=11&amp;q=immoral+jazz</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>'Hot Tamai
Makes Deb
Scrap Wc
amale., Tamale. she's Hot Tamale Mollie.
Laz gal through and through;
ks wiggles and wriggles,
hile ev'rybody giggles;
e likes her music blue.
Io' got a movement that's neat and
sweet
which she does not use her feet.
he's some baby!
'd rather shimmy than eat.
e hobbles and bobbles.
nd does some funny wobbles.
.111 she's out of breath.
h Golly! That Mollie
ll cure your melancholy
ad tickle you to death.
ch dancing never seen before
makes you holler out for more.
male. Tamale, Hot Tamale Moilie's on
the door.
ONLY JAZZ, THAT'S ALI.
No. that isn't a "hophead's dream."
'hat's jass.
It bears the edifying title of "Hot
amale Mollie," and is one of the
test jas; songs.
There's something else that goes
ith it; something that is written on
musical staff. It looks something
Ike music.
Jazz supporters say it Is music.
traight" musicians say it is unmiti
ted noise. Whether it is or is not
iuslc has not yet been decided. It
'robqbly never will. But, at any rate,
here is a most unharmonIoUs jangle
olng on In Washington musical cir
le over It.
For six days the musical warpath
ere has been trod beneath the hurry
ng feet of a rapidly swelling num
r of irritated musicians. Bands of
traights" and bands of Jazzers
allop hither and yon. bearing their
adly blowpipes and Addle bows.
fourly clashes occur.
Local orchestra lenders are In a
'dickens of a fix." They can't order
ag for fear of offending their
traight musicians. Neither can they
-der a classic wIthout incItIng their
zzers to mayhem and assault. Or so
ey fear. As a result, the local
-chestras are sIlent for the grea'ter
art of the twenty-four hours. True.,
ey always have been, but what of
at?
Congress hasn't taken the matter'
p,. but musicians say that It mightj
fit was in session.
In order that they may soothe their
rtured minds and work off some of
eir overpowering wrath, many nif
e musIcians ate playing violently
3cordlng to their "religion" in the
clusion of their homes.
TRUEC TO THEIR CULT.
The followers of the "Cult of Jazz"
ar loose wild howls and screams
om their trombones and horns and
aqally wild wails and shrieks from
eir violins and 'c'ellos. Unheard of
armonics and minor sesles rip up the
mT CLUB TO RESUME
LUNCHEONS TOMORROW
irt of Fall Serie. Will be in Form
of a Farewell Party to Louis
Browniow.
Members of the City Club wIll hold
eir first fall rally at 12:30 tomor
ow afternoon at the clubhouse, Far
'agut 14quare, when the we'kly forum
ncheons, whIch were discontinued
r the summer, will be resumed.
The initial luncheon will be in the
rm of a farewell piarty to District
ommissoner lamuis Browniow, who
aves Steptember 15' to become city
anager nt 1'etersburg, Va. Mr.
rownnw is an honorary member 'f
e club and has taken an active
terest in the organisation. flecause
fthe high esteem in which he is
w5, Va., aripp and confess
Of J. R. B. vis, who Bar
egterday, wkm chare of
his window. This 1oo
ton recently, when Austin
iLHis tra slt for the
Fe Mollie"
ut As Jazz
ixes Hotter
himney and seep through the win
tow frames and keyholes.
lext door, where the "straight'
OusIar- lives, the mmvb#r strairns 0
%e "Dead March" from Saul, or "Th
Dying Poet," reduce the family dog t(
Incoherent yelps and help lay th
lust.
But to the innocent bystander it
the street, whn is inflicted witi
equail portions of purple jazz and mu
sical solemnity, the effect is over
powering. The jazz goes In one ca
nd out the other. The funerea
ounds go in the other car and ou
the one.
It's the place between the ear
where the sounds meet and mingli
that hurts.
The fight between the jazz yn
sicians and the straight players wa
brought about a week agn tomorrov
by the filing of a breach of contrir
suit for $15,600 by Mario Armellin
formerly orchestra leader at th
Wardman Park Inn. against Harr
Wardman. Wardman said Armellin
couldn't play jazz and. therefor(
couldn't play for his inn patrons.
Another musician rose up and sal
that jazz wasn't music and tha
Armellinti couldn't he expected t
play it.
A musical critic came to the fror
with a tirade against jazz.
A "Jazz king" at Chesapeake Bear
read both the above statements an
spoke bitter words. "Jazz IS music,
quote he vehemently.
REPORK BUREAU MIXES IN.
Yesterday the International Refor1
Bureau took a hand in the pr(
ceedings. declaring jazz immoral an
a wicked waste of time.
Here's the latest effect of the cor
troveray:
The nusmher of jazrz phonograp
records sold here in Washingtoni ha
fallen off during the past week. ai
cording to prominent dealers. The
are not able to say' "whether this
due to the upheaval in musics
circles." but rather think that it ma
be so.
No decided increase, however.
reported in the sales of the classics
records.
'People seem to he tiring of jazz,
said one F street dealer. "This eor
trversy over jazz may help ti
public in getting ov'er the jazz idej
J don't know. Jtazz is more or le,
a fad. T believe, and it probabi
cannot last muc~h longer anywa:
,While it did last, though. reenr
sales were heavy. That will prn1
bly be made usp. If ts' jsazz dertir
is permanent. by increased sales
the better classes of music."</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1937-05-31/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=early+jazz+music</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045217/1922-03-29/ed-1/?sp=4&amp;q=early+jazz+music</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TWO SIDES OF THE JAZZ RECORD.
New York City, March 26.—A bitter
controversy over jazz has burst forth
in New York as the result of a recent
play by J. Hartley Manners, called
"The National Anthem," which treats
of the baleful effects of syncopation.
Jazz, according to those who champion
Mr. Manners' view, is a national curse
which is wickedly leading wholesome
Americans astray, while its defenders
insist that it is nothing more than a
pleasant, if banal form of amusement
and a healthful stimulating exercise.
Although this sudden assault upon
our one conspicuous contribution to
music may appear a trifle late now
that jazz in itB wildest state has passed
on to Europe and has been replaced
by a more refined phase over here, the
reform element is making the most of
it. A bill attempting to regulate
modern dancing and dance music has
recently been introduced into the New
York legislature, and will doubtless be
vigorously pushed through the law
making machinery in the near future.
Meantime, New Yorkers of prominence
including many in the theater and in
the pulpit, are eloquently voicing their
views on the subject.
"My objection to jazz." says Miss
Laurette Taylor, whose talent and
charming personality are making her
husband's play, "The National An
them" a great success, "is that one
can't sit still when it is played. You
just must get up and wear yourself
out dancing. When you become accus
tomed to the pronounced rhythm you
are unable to get that beautiful re
laxation which comes from the appre
ciation of fine music. ïhis is really
doing a terrible injury to young peo
ple."
Miss Ida M Tarbell, well known
author, holds a somewhat similar view.
"Jazz is to me a very irritating
thing," she declares. "It assaults the
nerves and dulls the brain. 1 do not
see how it can fail to have a demoral
izing effect if one subjects one's self
to it constantly. Drink is its natural
accompaniment. I have been across the
continent five times, and everywhere
on the streets and in the hotels I have
heard it. One could dance a great deal
to harmonious music, I should think,
and not have this terrible nervous ex
citement. But jazz is not music."
Jazz Cuts Down Booze
On the other hand Miss Margaret
Hawkeswortb, dance organizer, asserts
that jazz serves a high and noble pur
pose in diverting people and thus keep
ing them out of trouble. "I believe
that people would all drink more with
out. it,'' she says. "I see no connection
between jazz and drink except that if
there were nothing to do in the evening
people would be more likely to sit
around and drink. Jazz goes through
all classes of our national life and I
think it is here to stay. It is a god
send for both upper and lower classes."
This opinion is echoed 0 y Mrs.
Charles Tiffany, prominent New York
matron, who says: "It seems to me that
dancing has done more good than harm.
Older people exercise as they never did
before. People are more sociable,
more human. And after all. jazs af
fects only a fraction of the population.
Eighteenth century drawing rooqis
were just as much shocked by the waltz
aud other so-called round dances as we
are today at the ultra-modern steps
that accompany jazz music."
A nerve specialist quoted by a New
York newspaper considers jazz very
bad for the world in general, while a
well-known priest declares it as "rot
ten," leading to "all sorts of lascivious
dancing ana destroying whatever taste
for good music there might be."
Irving Berlin, who has made a fort
une in composing jazz hits, naturally
defends the product. "We live in a
jazz age," he points out, "and if you
don't like jazz you are out of tune with
the times. And a majority of people
must like it or it wouldn't be univer
sal throughout America, as it most cer
tainly is. Music reflects the thoughts
and habits of the people. There is
more freedom in social customs now.
Young women go about alone, everyone
is more independent, and all this is "duly
reflected in the music of the day."
Better Than Sentimentaltty
At least one serious composer also,
Miss Rebecca Clark, a young woman
whose compositions for the viola have
attracted favorable attention, takes a
generous view of jazz. "I like it for its
rhythm." she says, "and I consider it
better than the mawkish sentimentality
of the English ballads. At the last
analysis, jazz is only primitive rhythm
and in a way that is its trouble. It
makes a primitive appeal. Harmony
combined with rhythm gives us some
thing else to respond to and brings out
emotions of a different kind.'
In Europe, jazz is much more high
ly regarded than in this country, al
though its widespread popularity has
not been viewed by the bourgeoisie
without a storm of scared protest
Over there, however, it has aroused
much interest among nerious musicians
who at least respect originality. And
that jazz is an American product, in
spite of its supposed jungle origin, can
not be denied.
"But," says one European authori
ty. "if your serious American com
posers, through excess culture, con
tinue to ignore or sneer at jazz, they
may miss a very valuable opportunity
—the opportunity of initiating the next
great revolution in music. We may
discover over here that jazz will fur
nish to European music that infusion
of new blood and strength that is now
so necessary to its very life. In that
event, it may return to you Americans
disguised as 'modern music' with the
stamp of European approval which—
pardon me—seems so necessary to
your cultured classes in the United
States. In other words, what you now
despise and reject as vulgar, cheap and
contemptible, your musicians may ac
claim when eventually it reappears un
der a European label."
How Jazz Started
Meanwhile, jazz is undergoing a re
form in this country. It started out
in California a few years ago when a
young musician in the San Francisco
Symphony orchestra decided that he
wanted to get married, and that in or
der to accomplish the feat he would
have to have larger income than his
symphony salary. There was only one
thing for him to do—to take up dance
music. He did; and since then jazz
has never been the same. As a trained
way, much might be done to im
prove many factories, apecially
those engaged in industries of the
finer sort, where unjaded nerves
have the greatest economic value.
City life as a whole is still barbar
ously noisy and in some respects
perhaps grows worse, but the age
which has seen the advent of the
rubber tirt and the noiseless motor
may witness further developments
which will make the modern city a
fitter place for human existence."
and highly accomplished musician, he
began taking all the popular "blues"
songs and skillfully arranging them for
orchestration.
The average popular song consists
of merely one melody which is simply
repeated over and over again. Occa
sionally, at very rare intervals, a pop
ular song writer may grow extravagant
and combine a couple of melodies, but
this is regarded as unnecessarily
wasteful The one melody of the popu
lar song is the same as the theme of
classical music. Paul Whiteman was
the first to conceive the idea of taking
this one jazz melody and filling in the
gaps between its occurrence with
counter melodies. First comes a dra
matic introduction leading up to the
jazz melody, while after that each time
the melody occurs it is preceded by a
bit of—say a Liszt rhapsody or a
Chopin mazurka—^possibly even a dif
ficult passage by Bach.
According to Mr. Whiteman, this
task, which is now being followed by
nearly all the leaders of American
dance orchestras, is one which should
not incur the scorn of good musicians.
"All classical music," ne says, "con
sists, in the final analysis, of the folk
themes of peasants which have been
built into sophisticated art. With the
possible exception of McDowell and
Cadmen, our dance music has thus far
been America's one original contribu
tion to the music of the world. Our
other music has been the result of
European influences. And Europe
gives us credit for our contribution.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn79000083/1949-03-19/ed-1/?sp=8&amp;q=early+jazz+music</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Negro Gl’s Helping
To Win Jazz Fans
In Germany
Frankfurt, Germany Mar. 15—
American Negro soldiers joined
with a few youthful Germans,
are winning friends for “swing”
and jazz music in Germay.
Real American jazz has few
friends in this country of Bach,
Beethoven, Handel, and Wagner,
fans have formed “hot clubs" in
the larger, cities of Western Ger
many.
Frankfurt has the oldest club
with trumpeter Carlo Bohlaender
as Manager. Bohlaender, an old
timer in German jazz circles and
a recognized jazz teacher spent
two years in the United States
studying jazz from 1937 to 1939.
There is hardly a jam session
jn the Frankfur tHot Club with
out an American audience. Negro
soldiers of the American occupa
tion units, many of them profes
sional musicians often join the
band and “paint the house red,"
the club manager said
“Jazz is the most democratic
thing on earth," Bohlaender said
“because it teaches people of dif
ferent races and nations to un.
derstand each other ad to tolerate
each other’s thoughts and opin
ions"
Jazz usually is referred to by
Germans as “senseless noise-mak
i TIP TOP CLUB
t 0
{INVITES YOU TO COME OUT J
AND ENJOY FINE BARBE-
j QUE STEAK, CHOP
5 CHICKEN
Whitfield-Mill Rd.
Phone 2-5991 J
0 ELBERT TOPP, Mgr. J j
CHILDRENS
SEWING
DRAPERIES
and
BUTTON HOLES
DIAL 4-4744
Bar Jimcrow Cited
By Negro In Dis
barment Fight
Baltimore, Mar- 10 A Negro
attorey argue toay that the Bar
Assohiation. of Baltimore rannot
institute disbarment proleedi^gs
against him because it does not
permit Negro Members.
D. Lindsay Baynham is charged
mg’* which has nothing to do with
real music.” This attitude mayoe
a hangover from the Hitler era
when jazz was termed “un.Ger
man. decadent, and un becomin
to the people of a superior race.’
It fially was banned altogether.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn79000083/1944-01-08/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=early+jazz+music</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Says Ellington
Music 'Hybrid,'
Too Complex
l akes Crack
At Some Of His
Current Stars
By PAUL DANIEL DAVIS
BOSTON— (ANF)—Duke Elling
ton attracted a great mob to
Symphony hall in Boston on Sun
day night, with a thousand being
turned away. The Ellington con
cert in Boston was a difficult one
one to evaluate, with the band as
polished as ever, but Duke under
going a major change.
His compoitions and orchestra
tions become more and more com
plex, and he is turning to the mod
ern school of composition, retain
ing at the same time, much of I'ne
form of jazz, resulting in a unique
hybird. “New World A-Comin,’’
namer for Roi Ottley’s book of the
same name, seemed out of line as
a jazz composition, and not sat
is factory from any other standard.
The Piano interludes and clarinet
cadenza, particularly, had nothing
to do with jazz and nothing to do
with the rest of the composition.
MUSIC PERSONAL
As a known, Ellington’s music has
always been a very personal matter,
as far as he and his musicians
were concerned. Most of the ma
terial was developed by the entire
band, and only a few compositions
could truly be considered the sole
w»ork of any one man. The band
had an exceptionally stable per
sonnel between 1927 and 1941, but
the past two years have brought
about three or four times as many
changes as the Ellington band has
ever had. Results are that the
music is less distinctive, less per
sonal, and somewhat streamlined.
This is all too true when Ray
Nance, an ordinary trumpet play
er, a poor violinist, and an un
necessarily ever-pergforming show
man, is out in front as soloist. It
is not required that a violinst
assume an agonized, orgiastic ex
pression in order to produce
simple passage. Nance was such a
bad performer that when he came
out for his last violin solo the crowd
laughed before he even began
to play, Nance would have never
been tolerated in the old Ellington
band, and there would have been
no room for such ordinary musi
cians as Skippy Williams and
Jimmy Hamilton.
NANTON HIGHLIGHT
The highlight, of the evening wan
Joe Nanton’s coda on ‘Black and
Tan Fantasty.*^ Nanton’s plunger
trombone, although exploited some
times for comic effect is a favorite
in the Ellington band, especially
so since Johnny Hodges has taken
to playing only sentimentally, with
every appearance as a soloist wind
ing up in an ever-softening fadeout,
‘Rockin’ in Rhytm,” xvas a good
solid performance, and even Nance’s
fidle could not mar the beauty of
“Moon Mist.”
“Bakiff is a fascinating study
which perhaps belongs rightfully
in the same general category as
Starvinsky’s Shostakovich’s, and
even Ravel's ‘modern” composi
tions— superimposed on a steady
dance rhythm. The excerpts from
the ‘Brown” section of the much
discussed ‘Black, Brown, and Beige”
were most interesting.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn79000083/1944-09-16/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=early+jazz+music</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>Jazz Is Called
Strong Weapon
Against Hates
Color Forgotten
When Earthy Beat
Grips Hearers
By WILLARD MOORE
I For the Associated Negro Press*
An eminent peer of the arts
stated recently, “Jazz is a weapon
against fascism: it is an instru
ment for building interracial soli
darity; it is a tool that welds peo
ples together.
Let us examine this statement,
carefully probing and weighing;
j the evidence. We go into a ball
room or theatre where entertain
ment is lavishly waxed with the
music of good hot jazz. As we en
ter, the loud steady gutbucket
tempo reaches out and warmly
greets us.
RACES MINGLE
There are supple dancers, nim
ble jitterbugs hustiing, scurrying
about. A shrieking congregation of
people who, being merry, whirl in
thump-mad happiness.If you will
look close you will see harmonious
fluids of races intermingling—
black, white, red. brown, all color
1 ed, all creeds, some standing to
listen, others densely packed
shoulder to shoulder, breathing
with intense hunger the air of true
music.
There is much freCom here, lm
1 niense freedom for jazz. Plain,
simple folks dancing and listen
ing to a simple art. A folks’ art,
a people’s music. What prejudice
there may be in the person ebbs
swiftly. All diabolical thoughts are
miserably crushed. No thoughts of
hate reign. No battering of super
iority or inferiority against one
another. There is just Jazz. Pure
hot music pouring out, which
swells and boosts all hearts into
unification of goodness. There i«
love here.
COLOR FORGOTTEN
i Whether the musician be black,
white or any other color or nat
ionality, when he takes a solo,
showing his intrical e technique of
mastering his chosen instrument,
there is instantly spontaneous ap
plause showing appreciation. Not
because of the color of skin, but
because the virtuoso has produced
through his classic skill a primi
tive art which soars to its utmost
perfection.
Let me svate nere anu now that
if all people were to appreciate
persons solely because of merit in
any and all elements of life, that
itself would boost mankind. White
and black musicians gig together,
enjoying one another’s musical
performances, etc., which all in all
has resulted in mixed bands. Thus
we have greater music based on
ability. Here without doubt our
democracy is unfurled.
The musicians' recognition of one
another’s craft, their amiable es
teem of each other’s phrasing,
technique and individuality pro
vides the necessary shading and
contrast which enlarges each musi
cian’s scope and talent. This bor
rowing and giving brings them
closer together, further creating
the bulwarks of a true democracy,
and wings artist and audience in
to spheres of a united front.
Yes, jazz is mass music. A peo
ple’s voice revolting. A forceful
tool, fashioned, shaped and mold
ed from the torn hearts of slaves
into a striking weapon against
fascism oppression in America. Af
ter years of bondage, the dormant
hate of the bondsmen began pul
sating. Weird songs burst from
broken lips. Jazz! A musical pro
test sprang from split wombs of
misery. A mighty weapon had
come into being, a weapon that
will do its part in killing fascism.</text>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>


  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-new-york-city-skyscrapers</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn94052989/1892-06-13/ed-1/?sp=2/&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87062245/1902-07-20/ed-1/?sp=29/&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085488/1903-04-04/ed-1/?sp=9&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>UNIQUE FLATURtS IN SKYSCRAPERS,
Tiik Rkyscraper is an evolution, and o very recent one, from the com
paratlvely modesi structures of an earlier period. It is only fifteen
years since the ttrst of the type was planned, ami it originated in Chi
cago, which city claims the Tacoma Building, completed in 1889, as
the first American skyscraper. In all our large Cities, where foot front
values are enormous and constantly enhancing, the "Chicago construction"
id.-a, or the modem bridge built skyscraper, with Its skeleton of steel and
outer covering of stone, brick and gla>S (and which is riveted together so
firmly that Hie Cyclops might roll it down hill like a bird cape, if they
chose, without injury to its Structural parts, at once leaped into favor.
Other cities, notably New York, seised upon the idea, expanded and elab
orated it, and then began a rare as to which should build the tallest struc
tures, the tendency ever upward and with "excelsior" as- the motto.
Without any Intended disparagement of other cities, it may be safely
asserted 'hat New York now possesses more and larger skyscrapers than
any othe- city in the world. A decade or so ago Chicago was in (lie lead,
but now It is the great metropolis of the Empire State, wish its structures
of" steel +owerlng skyward by the score.
The tallest office buildings in the world are to be found in New York
City. Tt \v;i S thought the limit had been readied in the Park Bow or Syndi
cate Building, which, though nominally :>X2 feet in height, is 417 feet from
the street to the tops of the flagstaffa on its twiii towers and 501 from the
base of its foundations. It Is called the tallest office, bulldmg in the world,
its cupolas being 100 feet higher than the dome of the capitol at Washington
and almost as high as the apex of the great pyramid. And yet this great
structure, with its 0.10 rooms and accommodations for nearly 4,000 occupants,
stands upon a foundation of sand. Its total estimated weight: of 20,000 tons
is supported upon a forest of 12,000 piles driven into the sand by the blows
of a twenty ton driver. It cost $2,400,000 and is said to be a paying invest
ment—ln fact, there is hardly a skyscraper in New York, Chicago or any
any other city where realties are vastly valuable that Is not returning a gooil
rate of interest from its rentals. If it is not, then there is something the
matter, the experts say, with its management.
One of the most unique of skyscrapers, almost abnormal in its peculiari
ties. Is the so-called fiatiron structure at the Intersection of Broadway, sth
avenue and SM street. New York. Viewed from the front it appears rike
the bow of an Immense ship, being just wide enough at its edge fora narrow
window, yet. it is twenty-one stories high, rising 286 feet above the street,
and each floor of this stone and steel structure contains 8,300 square feet of
space. It cost $1,600,000. One of Chicago's latest and finest structures
Is Montgomery Ward Co.'s building. It contains twenty-one stories and
measures 31K) feet to the top of the weather vane.
One of the most sumptuously fitted of office buildings is said to be the
Frick skyscraper in Pittsburg, recently erected, which is twenty-two stories,
covers an entire block, has a floor area of 500,000 square feet and cost, with
the land it stands on, $4,250,000.
The erection of a five hundred foot skyscraper presents no greater diffi
culties to be overcome than that of a two hundred footer, for the structure
itself, considered geometrically, is a cumulative growth to which the genial 1
of years has steadily contributed. The building of skyscrapers is now an
exact science, and doubtless a structure could lie planned by our architects
that could be extended upward as far as desired. It has required a rapid
readjustment of the point of view to keep up with the growth of sky
scrapers, and the really unique features have become, like the articles enu
merated by the auctioneer, "too numerous to mention."</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85047084/1903-07-28/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A NEW SKY-SCRAPER
  The New York Times
i
fc-v W;r--;l -1 J :"-TiWwii ,Jai'-,-i -;iSss,u
is- -U; 5 iff! 'tfCf-Y ;5fl2 iMi 1 uawgv-Wi
tip-town from Newspaper Row. Its new home, which is being built at the junction of Broad
4 way, Forty-second Street, and Seventh Avenue, is to be the secood highett sky-scraper in the
city. Its summit will be 375
of the Park Row building, which holds the eky-scraping record for</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1904-10-30/ed-1/?sp=54&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>LOFTY OFFICE BUILDINGS.
The Tallest and the Narrowest Now
Being Completed in This City.
"Where will the audacity of the builder of sky
scrapers stop?" Such a question is likely to
arise in the mind of the most casual observer
-is he walks about the city. Within the last few
months several structures have been erected
which eclipsed any of their predecessors in the
boldness of their design, and just at the present
time two buildings are being completed in the
Wall Street district which would seem to mani
fest an especial contempt for the laws of
nature. Neither one has towers, and in
this lass of office buildings one is the
tallest in the world and the other is the
nairowest. Because of their extreme type
both present a most fantastic appearance. The
first has a rear addition twelve stories higher
than its front, and consequently looks as if
ready to turn a somersault. The second is so
thin that it resembles a gigantic soda cracker
stuck up edgewise.
Vet the builders of these skyscrapers declare
that they are far safer than the dwarfish, three
and four storied, old brick buildings that they
overtower. To these men neither one of these
buildings appears especially remarkable. Neither
one represents by any means the limit to their
daiing and skill. As one of them said:
"If it were not for the law we could build
them as tall as the Eiffel Tower, and that is
11. 1 feet high, or a little more than GOO feet above
the tallest skyscraper in New-York."
Ncr is this audacity confined alone to the
architect who plant? or the contractor who
"takes tin- job." Every workman Mem im
bued with this same characteristic. The riveter
may be seen climbing about the top of a steel
column some three hundred or more feet above
the street as nimbly as a monkey. Now and
then he will hang from that dizzy height with
only a bolthead under the toe of one foot, and
the other leg twisted around a crosspiece. Now
and then some workmen will go travelling sky
ward astraddle of a beam which is being hoisted
by the derrick on top of the steel frame, and
so unconcerned are they of danger that they
light their pipes as they sail aloft.
A comparison of some of the most recent sky
scrap, is with a few of the earlier ones shows
how much more audacious are the builders of
to-. than those of a few years ago. As soon
as the theory of the steel skeleton for tali struct
ures was discovered, about twenty years ago,
it was used to construct buildings of great
size, which ware regarded at that time as mar
vels of the builders' art. These structures,
however, spread more than they towered. The
ground area of some of them was tremendous,
and oven at the present time a few of them sur
pass all their more modern rivals in the size of
tie p round they cover. The Produce Exchange,
erected in ISM. which was the first large steel
cage building erected In New-York, covers more
land than any other ofP.ce- building in the city.
Its total ground area is r.7..V<() feet. Its height,
i M including its tower, is 130 feet. With the
touir it is S-~> feet hie.h.
In striking contrast with the Produce Ex
rini-.c Building is the Trinity Building, now in
tie loarse of construction at No. ill Broadway.
it shows how the present day builder piles up
bis structure, instead of spreading it out. Al
though its topmost oflice floor is nearly two
and a half times higher tlan that of the Prod
uce Exchange, it stands on a plol having an
r.verage width of 42 feet, or one-fifth :is wide
as tie exchange. The Trinity Building is Jl
stories high, an I, although it has only 11, .".us
Fo.ua- reel of ground area, leys than one-fifth
th.it if the Produce Xx change, it has a Boor area
of •_'I:_V».SSf.-,t, or more than ui:e-h;iif that &lt;.f the
exchange, which contains 401.430 square f t of
floor.
Tin building almost completed at No. C,&lt;) Wall
■t., Whirl] runs through to Pine-st.. haa ::r. o.Tic.'
floor VIA) feet abt.ve the street, or bighei than
that of any ott r towerten building I.i the
uorld. Tbis is the tw Mty-sixth Boor, and th.>
NEW-YORK TRIBUNE ILLUSTRATED SUPPLEMENT.
RIDING ON IKON GITtDEU 300 FKET UP IN THE AIR.'
Roof of the Washington Life Building in the background.
roof above is .'{4(s feet from the curb. Oa the
Wall-st. front the building is only fourteen
IT Ui 1!i| NT»-:WN T »-:W TRINITY BUILDING AT NO. 11l BROADWAY
i hi,- i he-,- l..riy iron mists the workmen climb like spiders.
stories, or 2iV_> feet hish. yet. In spite of this
handicap, the Hour area of 2Tr»,»>Ki feet la more
than twenty times Its ground area. The floor
area of the Produce Exchange is only a little
more than eeven times the ground space.
The Park Row Building, which with Its
towers reaches a height of 3SO feet, higher taaa
that attained by any other building in S v-
York or elsewhere, has a floor area twenty-si.i
times greater than that of the first story. Were
the Produce Exchange to obtain such a propor
tion, it would be necessary to pile upon the
present bul ling three more of like size.
In order to bring <>i t still more strongly th*
flatness of the old and the si in. ness of the new
style of office building, a few of the most striking
examples of each are given in table form. Mo-:
of the figures aro from ?peoi:ioa.t:ur-.d published
In "The Record and Guide."</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1904-10-02/ed-1/?sp=22&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>SOME VIE REMARKABLE NEW BUILDINGS tNNEW NEW NEWSKYSCRAPERS YORK YORKf
L
f SKYSCRAPERS GROWING BIGGER BIGGERMORE tsr fart s r r e p sr7t lt ANEWSTA ANEW A NEW STANDARD DARDSETFORTHEHO DARDSETFORTHEHOMORE SET FOR THE HO HOTELS H0MORE
MORE LUXURIOUS AND MORE MORECOSTLY y ty TELS TELSOFTHEWORLDBYTHELATEST TELSOFTHEWORLDBYTHELATESTCOSTLY OFTHE WORLD BYTHE LATEST LATESTOF
COSTLY THAN EVER BEFORE i r 3 OF THOSE BUILT IN NEW YORK
n
f
of
i lql i
aulo 0
There Tberewere were persons In this city not many manyyeanago many1earsago manyCeara
yeanago Ceara ago when the upward race in sky skyecraper skyaper skyaoraper
ecraper aper construction had hardly begun begunwho begunwho begunwho
who predicted that the excessively tall tallbuildings taUbuildings tallbuildings
buildings planned would not be successful successfuleither successfuleltheras euccesefuli
i either eltheras as money making properties or as aspractical asi aspraotical
i practical office structures structuresThe structuresTbelapeo structuresThe
The Tbelapeo lapse of if time baa proved prol l that these thesepersons thesePeJIIonswere thesea
a persons PeJIIonswere were mistaken Not only has the theskyscraper thekiscTaper theskyscraper
skyscraper turned out to be a success inevery in ineverjr Ineyel7Particular
every eyel7Particular particular except perhaps archi architecturally architexturally 1 1teCtumlly
texturally but it has come to be an absolute absolutenecessity absoluteD absolutenecessity
necessity D c Sslty
Whether Who er with the improved facilities facilitiesfor facilitiesfor
for rapid transit shortly to be available availableIn
1 In the city lty and with the enlarging of the thearea thearea thei
i g area of concentrated business activity that thathould thatllbouid thatshould
should follow as a natural result the sky skyscraper skyncraper skyscraper
scraper will continue to be as popular and andnecessary andneoessary andneoeeeary
necessary as it is now remains to bo seen seenbut seenbut seenbut
but In the opinion of many indicationspointto indications indicationspoint Indicationspoint
point pointto to the conclusion that It willIa will willIn V1lIn
In the buildings erected in the last two twoyears twoor twogears
gears years or so including some of the notable notablejonia notableODM
3 jonia sons ODM now in course of construction there therehas theroihM there1uishoen
has 1uishoen been li e 1 a noticeable notlc nble increase over tho thoprevious thoI theprpiloue
I previous p T1ous averago average In tho size and height heightj
i j i of f the structures structures Where two years ago agov agothere agothere
v there was but one Flatiron Building now nowthere nowthereare nowthere
there thereare are are two or three all just as remark retnnrkt remarkiltble
t iltble able In appearance as the one at Twenty lwent lwentthird
third street streetBuiwhlle streetBlltwh1etho streetButwhlle
Buiwhlle Blltwh1etho the office buildings have beengmsin been beengrowing beenJitrOWi
JitrOWi growing bigger blgg r8nd and higher they have It ItVlaYeald Itct
VlaYeald clald ct d been growing more costly the theYl theitiCrirdeea
1 Yl itiCrirdeea creoMjUVCost i cost t 1 In many many instances being beingnotaVall bllngj beingnet
j not notaVall a ata11proportlonate all proportionate to the Increase IncreaseIn
In alze This has been true too in spite spiteof spltoof spiteof
of the fact that tho general tendency re recently raciently rocently
cently has been to minimize external art artin artID i iIn
in the skyscraper and produce a building buildingEASY buildingBASY buildingi buildingBASY
BASY GRAFT OF THE MEDIUMSaHEIR MEDIUMS MEDIUMStTHEIR
i
aHEIR i tTHEIR VICTIMS DELUDED HI HIVEltr nrVEnJO RIVERY
VERY CHEAP TRICKS TRICKSTiothinv TRICKSothlnlf TRICKSTiothlnq
Tiothinv othlnlf Myitrrloo About the Means by byWWeTi b b111Icb bylt4r
WWeTi fl7t lt4r They 111e Play PIa on the Crrdulltv of off1 ori1
f1 r r Their Their Victim IcllmaA A Chicago Flrnii Irnl Mst Mstof IIstor iietof
of Mediums SUPIIIlesThelr Supplies Their Prior Priort
V t I suppose lU pose 1 1 have one of the queerest queerestfads qUoolIstfad
fads fadeon on earth said the man manoi1 oh on the hotel hotelBofal hott1t
Bofal t i My fy passion and nndhobby hobby Is mediums mediumsjdairyoyants nicdlumsi mediumsdairyY
i jdairyoyants SJaJ dairyY ioyants oanis psychic cant readers and andpthew aadtJieN andotheN
pthew tJieN of oUha that ilk Not that Im a spirltunl spirltunltat 6plrftualtat
tat The graft side of the medium business businesswhat bullinl88iIha businesswhat
iIha what interests me meThere meThere meThere
There are poor pickings for ine In New NowYork NewYork NewYork
York now because becau the be police poll polleeliavn ollIif have been beeninterfering hlCllinterfering beeninterfering
interfering with the medium it business businessBU11I l lnolll 4nerwstill lnolllBWII
BU11I still I can can find a cheap little test tt t circle hero heroalmost herebpo heroalmost
almost almost bpo t any time and a d I Level even ev know known a place placejust pIaIXi placejail
i just off tho Tenderloin Tend rloln whomyol whcrp you r 1 can C lJI see seereal seeral eo eor
r real ghosts developed in full v1e view r of tho thoaudience thoait theaudlenco
audlenco audience ait enco To see CO it In full blast hln t though thoughyou th01lphoumu thoughy
y you you oumu must t go to Boston BO ton or better to nIl Far FarWestern FarWeetcrn FarWestern
Western cities citiesMost cltlcelof08t citiesc
gr Most people suppose that mediums all allprofess allf allF
c f profess to summon up real ghosts ghoststhat that thatJn thatm
i Jn the lip language of tho profession prorM lon they theytnatoriaHze tho thon theyr
r a rflatFrtalize tnatoriaHze n r1allzo That Isnt true To ono ma materlailtng mnteriaUzng materlalltitg
terlailtng medium In these days there are area arej ares
s j a hundred test mediums mediumsThe medlumRTho mediumsThe
The test medium holds forth usually usuallyin IIHllall IIHllallIn
in a cheap hall The admission nchnl lon Is I low lowfor lowfor lowy
y for herpatrons are poor Usually it runs runsfrom runsfrom runsr
r from 10 to 25 cents centsl centShe
l She ftorta rts off with u hymn Then she sheborrotq BVJ BVJborrow Rhoborro
borrow borrotq an article from each person In Inthe IIIthetiongrcgntlon Inthe
the thetiongrcgntlon congregation and iMgliys her tests testsFor teRtIFor testsFor
For cxamplo shell hold up a glove gloveand gloveand gloveand
and ask who owns it When the owner ownerbaaspoken ownerhaa ownerhaa
baaspoken haa spoken up shell hold tho glove to her herforehead herforehead I Iforehead
forehead and say sa something like this thisI I II
I hear the name John Have you a aI aft
ft ftI5aA I
I5aA
r ra
t r z
1HAUOVER HANOVER NATIONAL BAHH BANIfll 8ANXPfG7q
fll PfG7q 71P CaPYprGHr IPYFfIlTIfv yv u JH fON N Y
with little expression of architectural architecturalform architecturalform architecturalform
form formThe formThe formThe
The Increased cost It is said resultsfrom results resultsfrom resultsrrom
from the more elaborate and substantial substantialfinishing RubRtnntlalflnlsl subatantlalfinishing
finishing flnlsl ng of the Interior and the more com complete complete complete
plete equipment of the building with all allports allIIOrts allsorts
ports of modem Improvements For instance in instance inIltanCt
stance many of the recent skyscrapers skyscrapersbesides skyscrapersbesides kyscrapersbeflldl8
besides having all the usual sanitary sanitaryequipments snnltaryI
I equipments have Installed the vacuum vacuumsystem vacuumsystem vacuumI
I system of sweeping sweepingI sweepingLines
I I Lines of hose run from vacuum hydrants hydrantsin
in the corridors Sweepers are attached attachedto
j to the hone and by running them over theoffice the theoffice theoffice
office rug the dirt is transferred in a twlnk twlnki twinkling
i ling from the room hundreds of feet in ini
i I the air to the basement basementThis bnsementI basementThis
This is only one of the many modern modernconveniences modernconvenipnces modemconveniences
I conveniences which the business man of oftoday oftoday oftoday
today expects to find in these great build buildings hlllldthat buildingsbuildings
ings ingsbuildings buildings that count their occupants occupantsby
by h the thousand thousandthat that alone constitute in insome InlOme insome
some cases an entire route for a letter car carrier carI carnor
I rier nor and from which wl ch the dally mall is car carried carI carTied
I Tied not by hand but by b the wagon loadThe load loadThe loadI
I The skyscraper has always al Ys been a thorn thornin thornin
in the flesh to the architect nrchitecttho the student studentof
of the thebeaux beaux arts ar and the man who wants wantsfrankness wantsfrankneK8 wantsfrankness
frankness of expression In his design designThese de8lgIlThese designThese
These men complain that there is no noI noattempt
I attempt in the American skyscraper to tomake toI tomake
make its I appearance express its structure structureIt
I It la a lie an uncouth lie from the founda foundation toundatlon foundation
tion to the roof they the say fIa Seeking to toI
I hide tho fact that It is built around a steel steelI steelframe
I frame it simulates solid masonry masonryNearly Inl1lOnr Inl1lOnrI masonryNearly
I Nearly Xearl all of them sin ln in tho nine wny wnythese wnythese waythese
these architects say the buildings having havingthe havingthe havingthe
the general appearance of n column with witha
a heavy base a long Ion I central shaft and a adecorated adecorated adecorated
decorated capital C What they would have haveJohn haeJohn haveJohn
John In tho spirit world worldIf
If the ho owner of tho glove has a John Johnamong Johnamong Johnamong
among tho departed the th medium sends sendssome sendssome end endome
some beautiful communications and then thentries thentries thentries
tries to draw the victim out With a clever cleverness cleerneSlS cleverness
ness born of experience she pieces to together together together
gether his occupation his hi troubles and his hiswants hiswant hiswants
wants and tells him all about them themHes thllIIHeR themHes
Hes paralyzed with astonishment and andso andso andso
so are tho rest of the circle circlefor for the people peoplewho peoplewho peoplewho
who go to usances f ancel arent critical and they theygo theygo theygo
go with a great desire to believe bellevnOne b1I9voOno believeOno
Ono of tho hardest things for a test testmedium tClltmedium testmedium
medium to do is I to call at once the name nameof lIameor nameof
of the dear departed in the spirit realm realmIT
11 11silo IT she star starts t on with John and runs nmllthrough through through1r
Mhry 1r af a atid d 1 ji Kntherlno ana Lily and none noneofthetn noneoruielll noneoftheni
ofthetn hits the mark then the most crodu crodunounce
lOUR seeker after Hlrltil I Is inclined i to pro pronounce pronounco
nounce her a fake On tho other hand
If she fits at opts the name of tho very veryspirit veryspirit ery
spirit which hlch tho seeker most desires shes shespronounced flhe flhepronouncerl shespronounced
pronounced a great success successTheir successTheir UCffThelr
Their host II t means of getting ttlnlt at names
h 11 a sort of Mediums Union an unorganized unorganizedsociety unor unorganizedecpciety nnlzcd nnlzcdKOClcty
society for mutual help which exists IX lilts In Ineven1 Inwln Ineren
even1 medium ridden town townblme
Mme Fake oakl the medium has n now nowvisitor no novRltor nowvisitor
visitor n fat woman in black well nay naywho MYwho saywho
who wears her front hair In gray frizzes frizzesami frlT7e11nnd frizresand
and has u I slight limp Mine aka tries triesout trllout triesout
out a half n dozen names nam on her Perhaps Perhapsshe
she If get gets down to the sixth I th before sho ho finds findsthat flmlllthat findsthat
that Robert fits some dend relative of the theold theolel theold
old lady in black blackBefore binckJleroro blackBeforn
Before Mm Fake get gets through olios
learned further that the old lady has a dead deadslttor dlaelRItr deadsl4er
slttor named Annie Tim old lady re remeinlwlng roo roomrnlllrlng romembering
meinlwlng how long Mine Fake has hn been
In getting Ittln those names goes away aa away do dodaring doclarlng doGlaring
daring that shes flhIIIU tio namltll good goodMrs 100l 100llrs goeelMrs
Mrs lrs Fake I nke knows all that and knows knowsthat knowlIthat knowsthat
that the old lady wont come here again againhut altalnbul againhut
hut that shell 6ha11l1urcly surely go to another medium mediumfor mtdlumfur
fur when a poison K1on In I bitten by the spirit spiritualistic RplrltunlltlC spiritunlistic
ualistic bug h usually IIHunll keep going to med mediums modhum msvlfums
hum until he gets satisfaction satisfactionSo
So Mrs Fake notifies every 6er medium
In her crowd giving a close clOf O description descriptionof fe cription criptionof
of the old lady together with thenames thenamesof the names namesof namesof
of her spirit friends and any nn other accurate accurateInformation aocurateInformation aoeurateinformation
Information which she ho has been able to todrag todrag todrag
drag out Next Sunday night when hen am amold anold ansold
old lady ady in black with frizzes and a limp limpJ
5 5r
J
r 13 J rr r r rr
i J HOTEl OTf ASTOR
1 kT S
NDr Y
R GlS WAG
of the skyscraper If it really resl1 must be and andthey andthey andthey
they admit that it must is i a franker ex expression oxpreeslon lXprl8slon
pression of tho fact that then Is I beneath beneaththo benraththo beneaththe
tho covering of stone and brick a frame frameof framoor frameof
of steelThere steel steelThere teelThere
There is I ono building in the city clt com completed COIIIplltf completecl
pleted plltf 1 only about a a year eur ago which archi architects anhitec arrhttocts
tects tec agree la I more successful Rucet jrul in thN thi re respect r rsped respect
spect than most others It Is called callC t one oneof oneof oneof
of the few reI successful ICl flll skyscrapers archi architecturally architecturally i itecturnlly
tecturally regarded In the city cityIt elt cityIt i
It Is tho Blair Building at Broad road street streetand streetand trretand
and Exchange place A picture of it is isincluded I IIncludC isIncluded
included 1 In the group above Its successlies success HUCCLSDlies I IICClMlies
lies chiefly chien In tho fact that it does not simu simulate shnulate 111111late
late solid masonry Its frame of steel Kteclis I steelis teelIs
is not openly disclosed I but some of the thometal themetal themetal
metal column are permitted to show in intho Intho inthe
tho facade facadeshows fa facadeshows ade adeshow6
shows up at the Homo of Truth Circle Circleconducted Circlecunducted Circleeflductal
conducted by b Mrs lrA Koakom Soakentthe the second secondsight HIlondII secondsight
sight II ht wonder the old lady Iud is told right rightoff rightoff rightoff
off tho but that Robert wants her and a abeautiful abeautirul abeautiful
beautiful spirit named Anne Is over her hershoulder hlrIhoulder hershoulder
shoulder calling her sisterShe sister sisterSho sI8tfrSho
Sho goes g away firmly 1111111 convinced that thatMrs thatMrs thatMrs
Mrs Soakem is I a wonder and that immortality immor immortality Immortnlft
tality tnlft is proved In a Western city elt Ive Ivewen 10n Iveseen
wen n printed blanks used to distribute dlRlrl ute such suchinformation HuchInrormntion suchinformation
information among mediums mediumsThat rnedinmsThat
That isnt their only nly method or prttiK peltirgnames prttiKnames prttllgnmnCR
names though Some of them an very veryclover veryclover ry ryclever
clover lipreaders When hll1 In doubt dOli hI they theyplay the thepia theyplay
play pia William or John those tho being tho thomost thomOl themost
most mOl t common AngloSaxon AfI loHaxlm namesThen names namesThen nnmeThln
Then they the make it a point to liarn the thonames thnnameR thenames
names of peopln III plo living in the neighborhood neighborhoodand
and to watch the obitimry nfdices knowing knowingthat knnwirlltthat knowingthat
that half their victims ore driven to themby them themby
by 11 the ache of Homo recent cnt bereavement bereavementThais 1 bereavementThats aemllIt aemllItThatH
Thais the nasty part of the whole busi business hUIInl Inisinews
ness The laboring mens wives 1m and andduuigh andduuighters daugh daughters dllllghte
ters te 111 tho hired girls and stable tabl boys who whohaunt whohaunt whohaunt
haunt cheap sonatas F anltK cwno Ixcauso weause theyre theyrein IhlroIn
in trIIblo trail bio anil want some help and ennsolntion consola consolation conl oln olntlon
tion These people nut their hearts on ontheir 011thllr ontheir
their HleovoA and tell alxv1 their love loveaffairs InpalTaiill loveaffairs
affairs and family difficulties dl ffieu It If in n way waythat wa wathnt waythat
that makes you gasp 1 blush sometimes sometimesto 01111 hlls hllsto
to listen to them thetaThe themTho thmnThl
The cheap text anee hnN inoo isnt II the plnc plncwhore liic liicwhero
whore the mediums InI rood dlllTl Iumn make their noneythough money moneythough II OllW OllWthouvh
though It is I really rC lly only 0111 nn advertisement advertisementto advert isenunt isenuntto
to got custom for the privitte und develop
ing seancoH l aeanecs i1I1C All hilI thn 1 ho time she Is I sending sendingcomtnunlrntlons sendingromnrunicnliona llIlIn llIlIncommunlrlltlon
comtnunlrntlons to her audici audience nl1111 lIO e she is issizing I I17lnl issizing
sizing 17lnl them up If ono looks morn easyor easy easyor eIL eILor
or eager than the rot she ho hays nlIlomcthlnlt something
like this thisJohn thl thlJohn thisJointtelIsinnllint
John JointtelIsinnllint tells trll inn t ihat lint t thl thoapIritshave he spirit plritH havo much nnirhto muchto
to tell you ou but youio OUIO holding heel You Youno YOIIn Veilnetl
no n netl d todmw to Brow closer do fr to em emThat pmThnt pinflint
That suggestion t IH If thrown out once or ortwice ortwlI ortwirn
twice About the third tlmo this thl particular particularvictim pUltllulnrvlrtlrn particularvictim
victim visits hllt the poance 6IIe the spirits says saysWt sny n nWcIHInorn
WcIHInorn Wt Vo have something thlnltttell to tell you that thatCnnt thatCnntbo cant cantbo canth
h bo o told in public You must see n 1 medium mediumalone IIIrdlumalone riietilutnalone
alone aloneI
Ir I f the victim Is I a woman womannnd and sho ho usually Ulmall UlmallIRcurlolIh
Is IRcurlolIh curiosity brings IJrin R her around the very verynext verynext Iry Irynext
next day Tin privatu sittings cost from fromSO frontSo
SO cents an hour up according nccor lng to the mean meanand mlllnand meansand
and credulity credullt of the victims The me medium medlum medium
dium loses no chance of loading her on to tocome tocom toooma
come again againDeveloping
Developing sittings aro a 1 beautiful beautifulgraft beautifulIratt beautifulgraft
graft The medium uses this dodge on onr
r 4 1 r
But while some architects deplore the conventional con conventional convcntlonal
ventional and what they cull inartistic inartistictrend Inartlstlotnmc inartistictrend
trend in skyscraper architecture they the ad admit admit admit
mit that it U I tho most notable and the themost themot themost
most thoroughly American architecture of oftlm otthp ofthe
the time and that it affords an opportunity opportunityfor opportunltfor
for tho earning of the largest fees ever everobtained everoht everobtained
obtained oht alnll by b architects in general practice practiceSo
So far as IL the height of the office building buildingof
of tho future is concerned there is II it in insaid II IIII1ld issaid
said practically no limit below CO or 70 70stories 70torie 70stories
stories torie imposed by byeconomical economical or structural structuralconsiderations IItructuralcon structuraleonsideratlmm
considerations con icleratlonR All that will las lx necessary necessaryis nfCfI nr nrIR
is a FUfllcient amount of space for tho foun foundations foundation</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1905-06-24/ed-1/?sp=24&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>ERA OF SKYSCRAPERS
Skeleton Construction Began
Seventeen Years Ago.
PIONEER STRUCTURE

THE MULTIPLE USES OF THE TALL
BUILDINGS.

First Built for Office Purposes Exclu
sively, but Now for Homes,
Schools and Factories.
Written for Tho Star.
Seventeeen years ago next Tuesday the
work of construction was begun on the build
ing which made the skyscraper possible.
Within the next few weeks the work of
tearing1 it down will be under way, and on
the site will be erected a twenty-story office
building at an estimated cost of a million
and a half dollars.
This pioneer structure, whose days are
numbered. Is known as the Tower building,
is located at 50 Broadway, New York, and
is generally recognized among architects
and constructing engineers as embodying
the first radical application of a thorough
going system of skeleton construction, the
essential of the skyscraper.
In some quarters It may still be held that
this distinction does not rightfully belong
to the Tower building. For many years
after its construction a hot discussion was
years In New York eighty-six buildings,
ton stories and over In height were erect
ed, and yet, notwithstanding the efforts on
the part of many builders to put up ex
ceedingly high buildings, the average height
of each of the eighty-six buildings was only
thirteen and a half stories.
These three years saw the erection of the
highest skyscrapers to date. Since then the
tendency has been to erect buildings more
on a level, as the figures for 190:1-4 and the
present year up to May show. During this
period there hsive been constructed In New
York 111 buildings of all descriptions ten
stories high and over In altitude, with an
average height of a fraction over twelve
stories, the fraction not being sufficient to
permit of a garret of even small dimen
sions.
In this connection It Is worth noting that
during these years only seven buildings
above fifteen stories have been erected, of
which four have sixteen, two eighteen and
one twenty-six stories, respectively. From
18St5 to ISA", Inclusive, fifteen buildings over
fifteen stories In height were erected, divid
ed as follows: One thirty, one twenty-six,
one twenty-one, two twenty, one nineteen,
five eighteen and four sixteen stories.
This lessening of the heischt of sky
scrapers is being explained In this fashion:
Every story added to a building means In
creased elevator service. That means, besides
Increased cost of operation of the building,
decreased income from renting, for more
space must necessarily be given over to
elevator shafts. Time has pretty thorough
ly proved that a skyscraper is not the
money-maker it was thought at first it
would be. In fact, the owner of a sky
scraper who makes 3 per cent on his in
vestment should think himself lucky. So,
It can readily be seen why the tendency of
latter years has been to bring down the
average height of skyscrapers below that
of ten years ago.
Skyscrapers as Advertisements.
But if skyscrapers are proving to be
not very profitable Investments, why are
they being built in ever-Increasing numbers
throughout our large cities? It Is a
natural question; and the answer consists
of several parts. In the first place, they
must be built, willy nilly, that the workers
may have places In which to work In such
cramped-up cities as New York and Pitts
burg. In the second place, they are >ooked
SKYSCRAPERS IN VICINITY
waged as to whether the Tower building
was the pioneer, many claims for this honor
being made by the architects of other build
ings erected either shortly before or about
the time that Bradford L. Gilbert, as archi
tect, filed the plans for the Tower building.
Of recent years, however, there has been
little or no disputation concerning the
Tower building's right to the distinction.
This change was brought about largely by
the careful and thorough investigation con
ducted to settle this mooted Question by
The Real Estate Record and Builders'
Guide of New York city In 1898. This is
what that publication, an authority broad
ly recognized, had to say:
Skyscraper's Origin.
"Numerous claims have been made for
the Invention of the system of skeleton con
struction. The Idea of using Iron In some
form for the vertical support of buildings
was in the air In the middle of the eighth
decade. Iron columns and beams had, ol
course, been frequently employed in in
terior positions. The novelty embodied In
skeleton construction consisted in applying
iron to the exterior as well as the interior,
and developing the metal framework thus
arrived at into a consistent and radical
system of support.
"In 1884 W. L. B. Jenny of Chicago, in
designing the Home Insurance Company s
building in that city, employed a system of
cage construction?that is, the outer walls
were built self-sustaining, while the floors
and roofs were carried on an independent
iron framework. This, however, was not a
thorough-going system of skeleton construc
tion. So far as we know, the honor of
making the first radical application for
the new method belongs to the New York
architect, Bradford L. Gilbert, who filed
plans on April 17, 1888, for the Tower build
ing 51) Broadway, wherein he proposed to
use the exterior cast-iron columns, eighteen
feet apart, to carry the floors, instead of
the usual solid brick walls. For a time
there was some doubt as to whether the
building department would sanction this
novel method. Conservative views, how
ever were overcome, and the work of con
struction was allowed to commence June
27 1888. The building was completed fif
teen months later. This is the pioneer
utrueture of its class, and fixes for us the
Beginning of the really modem era of the
office building
"The novelty of the new Idea was merelj
one of application, for the skeleton frame,
from the mechanical point of view, is noth
ing but a bridge set on end, and protected
externally from the weather by a curtain
wall of masonry. This new application,
however, was revolutionary. It was adopted
with remarkable alacrity by architects and
owners, and promptly resulted In an aver
age addition of five stories to the height of
office buildings. Within the last two or
three years the tendency has been toward
greater altitude, and so far the net result
of the skeleton construction has been to in
crease the height of buildings to about
double the limit made possible by the in
troduction of the elevator."
The practical height made possible by the
elevator, under the old system of construc
tion, in which the exterior walls were made
to support the weight of the floors, was
nine stories. Between the date of the ap
plication of the elevator to office buildings,
in the late sixties, to the Introduction of the
skeleton system of construction, the height
of office buildings had increased gradually
from five and six stories, as the elevator
was improved and its possibilities more
realized. But when the altitude of build
ings had been run up to 150 feet, approxi
mately, it was found that the walls, In
order that the floors might be properly sup
ported, would have to be considerably in
creased in thickness, and they were so
thick already and taking up so much valu
able real estate that the owners were con
stantly complaining that the renting space
was being cut down too much and the
buildings were not the paying investments
they should be. Hence, the casting about
of architects to find a way to overcome
this difficulty, a search which finally led
to the standing of a bridge on end and in
closing it with "a curtain wall of masonry"
as a protection from the weather.
New Light on Height of Skyscrapers.
But though it has been highly practicable
since the construction of the Tower build
ing to run up buildings to heights undream
ed of before, and there are structures vary
ing from twenty-five to thirty stories in
altitude above the surface, it is a note
worthy fact that the average height of all
buildings above the practical limit possible
under the old system of construction Is far
from being what one would naturally sup
pose it to be after spending a day looking
upward at the towering structures in the
business centers of such cities as New
York. Chicago, Philadelphia and Pittsburg.
It was during the three years immediate
ly prior to the outbreak of the war with
Spain that there seemed to be a mania in
New York for putting up record-breaking
structures, in the point of altitude. Then
were constructed the Park Row building,
the highest office building in the world;
the St. Paul building, almost as tall: the
Empire building, and many others whose
course of construction was followed pretty
generally all over the country with much
wonder and comment. During thee* tfcref
OF THE TOWER BUILDING.
upon as conservative and sure Investments
by many persons who have tired of strenu
ous money earning; and In the third place,
many are built largely for purposes of
advertising.
When the day of the skyscraper had fully
arrived shrewd men were not long in
realizing that here was a splendid oppor
tunity to attract attention to themselves
by putting up the highest buildings yet
erected by human hands. They knew that
this feat would be heralded far and wide,
for from the moment the skyscraper came
into existence it caught the popular fancy,
and the public could not hear too nruch
about it, apparently. So, In order to ad
vertise their businesses in a novel way,
these shrewd men began running up sky
scrapers. One of the first advertising
"scrapers" to be built was the World
building in New York; it was talked about
all over the country and had a great deal
to do with making the name of the World
known in quarters far distant from the me
tropolis. Then financial institutions took
up the advertising scheme, and great
bank buildings, twenty and twenty-five
stories in height, made their appearance.
Of recent years hotel managers have been
boasting in print of the numerous stories
of their hostelries; and they, as well as*
such rich financial concerns as great
national banks and life insnrance companies,
have also striven for further publicity by
spending immense sums of money on the
exterior and interior decorations of the
"scrapers." To say that the walls of a
"scraper" afford opportunity for all sorts
of gingerbread work that will catch the
eye is putting the situation mildlj Archi
tects declare that they have not been able
to evolve a rational "scraper" to date, be
cause of the demand of owners for build
ings which will catch and hold the eye and
be talked about regardless of artistic or
aesthetic considerations.
Contest in High Buildings.
The desire to be known as the builder and
owner of the highest building in town, and
Incidentally to benefit therefrom In a busi
ness way, has led to some amusing results.
Shortly after the first "scraper" was
erected in Philadelphia, on the northeast
corner of Broad and Chestnut streets, in
the middle nineties, Brewer Fred Betz de
cided to steal the trust company's thunder
From Funcb.
"UNFORTUNATEI
by putting up atonfstd# of It building
several stories higher. When hie plans
were filed, the fact was wisely heralded
chat the tallest building yet In the Quaker
city was shortly to be got under way.
At once there was a mighty scurrying
about of the trust company's officers, and
as Boon as architect's plans could be made
there came the announcement that the
trust company's building would receive an
addition of several stories, making It the
highest building.
By this time the Bet* building had been
all but completed, and the rival owners
felt that, since the work had got so far
along and Mr. Bets would be anxious to be
getting a return on Ills Investment as soon
as possible, he would not niter his plans.
But they reckoned without their host, for
within a few weeks there came the news
that two more stories would Ik> added to
the Bel* building, thus making It the high
est building in town after all. It was at
tihls point that the trust company gave U4>
the contest, and the Bet* building remain
ed the tallest office structure in Philadel
phia for nearly a decade.
Dire Prophecies.
Equally amusing as this rivalry, which
still exists in some quarters, though not
with its former Intensity, are the recol
lections of the dire prophecies made about
the "scrapers" in the days of their advent.
When the puny little Tower building?ten
narrow stories In height?was going up,
thousands of people dally gathered about
It to watch the remarkable system of con
struction and to tell of all the mishajts
which would certainly befall the persons
who were foolish enough to occupy It.
Then, when the really high building came
In and passers-by beheld story after story
topped. It was said that .the first hard
blow would send the whole structure top
pling earthward: that It would collapse of
Its own sheer weight, and that the persons
who ventured on the upper stories would
surely be blown out of the windows by the
strong upper currents of air.
Imleed. in New York, several Arms, when
they took offices on the higher floors of the
initial scrapers, found many of their
clerks missing the first morning, and these
fearful ones were not all women, either.
There were numerous Instances of men and
women nil but dragged to their new office
under threats of dismissal, and dally, for
many weeks, there were demonstrations of
the stability of the buildings and of their
occupants on Uhe top floors. At first the
top floors were the last to be rented, for
not a few heads of firms and professional
men were nervous about going so high In
the air to earn their bread. How different
from today, when the scramble Is all for
the higher floors, 1n order that the best
light may- be obtained and the noise and
con'fusion of the streets escaped as much
as possible.
Utilized for Many Purposes.
In the first days of the tall building It
was limited exclusively to office purposes.
Even as late as the latter nineties the or
flce building predominated. For the throa
years beginning with 1S95 there were erect
ed In New York forty-five ofllce buildings
ten stories and over In height, eighteen
stores and lofts, five flats and apartment
hotels, eleven hotels, six warehouses nnti
factories and one printing house. The to
tal number was eighty-six the office build
ings being two over half the total.
Since the beginning of the present cen
tury this state of affairs has materially
changed. Instead of being largely limited
to ofllce purposes, the sky-scraper Is bWng
extensively utilized for all sorts of hous
ing purposes. This Is proved by the figures
of the building bureau of New York for the
years beginning with 1{*?, during which
thirty-six stores and lofts, twenty-four ho
tels. seventeen flats and apartment hotels,
fifteen office buildings, eight factories three
warehouses, two studios, two clubs, one
hcspital. one printing house, one sot of
college dormitories and one public school,
all ten stories and over, have been built.
Until within the last five years "It was
hardly possible to find a building over eight
stories in New York above Centra' Park.
Now there are scores of apartment houses
In this section varying all the way from
ten to fourteen stories in height, Central
Park West and Broadway, between the
sixties and 110th street, are plentifully
sprinkled with these skyscraper dwellings,
and more are being erected continually.
Towering Apartment Housea
The fashion for towering apartment
houses came in with the building of the
Ansonia, fourteen stories, in the last year
of the last century and the first two years
of this. Before that, one or two buildings
similar in character, but not so high or
commodious or elegant in finish, had pong
up, but they had been looked upon pener
ally as being sporadic, and It was not uni
versally realized that such tall dwellings
would pay until the owner of the Ansonia
demonstrated that there were more than
enough people In New York by several tena
of thausands to pay the high rentals neces
sary to make such structures profitable in
vestments.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87093029/1906-04-27/ed-1/?sp=7&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>TALLEST SKYSCRAPER
IN THE WHOLE WORLD.
Engineers, architects, and bulldem
everywhere are Interested In the plana
made public from New York for a
skyscraper that will out skyscrape
anything yet built. These plans were
filed with the New York building de
partment by Ernest Flagg, for the
proposed Singer building. Nothing
more radical has ever been attempted
on either side of the ocean than Is
embodied in the plans for this struc
ture. The building is to be forty
stories high and other buildings in New
York and Chicago which now causa
people to become stiff-necked looking
up at them will, by comparison, appear
small.
Two of the tallest Chicago buildings,
the Masonic Temple and the Majestic
Theater, would be but one story high
er than the Singer building, if on*
was placed on top of the other. There
will be 595 feet of the structure above
ground and probably 125 feet of It
below the street surface, bo that, all
told, it will be ten feet longer than the
mammoth* Amerlka, the .biggest steam
ship afloat
It was supposed the limit bad been
reached in this style of structure, but
it seems not Before long a fifty story
pile may be expected to make slow go
ing people gasp.
While Chicago was the pioneer in the
erection of tall buildings, it has tn
the last few years been far outstrip
ped by New York. The constantly in
creasing population of Manhattan Isl
and and the impossibility of increas
ing the ground area for the accommo
dation of the people made it neces
sary to run the buildings higher and
higher until it is impossible to tell
when the limit will be reached.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1912-01-21/ed-1/?sp=61&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Marvelous Vertical Railways in the New Woolworth Building That
Are to "Whiz" the Army of Workers Up With Lightning Speed
726 Feet in the Sky in Absolute Safety and Comfort.
fillS
mmmtmm
$'T lil iigiill
'!3?-r.-ftaCM WMff the marts
ISWS Mr I SSBH JJ.I i 3 iffif) IWWJ1 and
Wilier TPiil
Sill Pil l liill'IS
m WWM Wmmm? a IIS
SINCE the world began one characteristic has always
been dominant in mankind that is, the desire to
create to construct abodes -places of business to
build something that would serve for comfort or con
venience, or a monument to his greatness, individually
and collectively. Through the ages this characteristic
has dominated more and more, until to-day the in
ventive and creative genius of man seems without limit.
Every civilized country on the globe is marked with
cities exemplifying the almost perfect constructive genius
of human mind and hand. Invention has always stood
ready to meet every rising necessity. In no other
respect is this so strikingly shown as in the develop
ment of the modern "skyscraper," with its concentrated
economic facilities. Everywhere majestic buildings pinnacle
the sky. Every Art and Trade has contributed to these
creations, but no ONE thing has been of so vital import as
has been the invention of elevators, making each floor,
regardless of elevation, equally accessible and livable. No
feat of engineering science is more wonderful or of
more worldwide usefulness than the invention of
elevators.
Klevators are the OXE thing that has made possible the construction
of the Titanic structures of stone and steel that everywhere to-day dot
of Trade and Industry. The ONE thine that has heightened
ine," and marvelously increased the land values of the world's
greatest cities, insuring to them unlimited develop
ment, concentration, and prosperity.
There have been recorded in the world a large
number of inventions calculated to solve the problem
of passenger and freight elevation, but it remained
for an American institution The Otis Elevator
Company, 17 Battery Place, New York to perfect
bring to the attention of the Commercial and
Industrial worlds elevator inventions that meet every
exacting requirement, and that render the highest
effective and economic service.
The achievement of this Company in perfecting
the highest type of elevators has gained for its product
recognition as the standard of excellence throughout
the civilized world, and it is fitting tribute to the
superior quality of their product that Otis Elevators
should have been chosen (as has been the case in
nearly every other renowned building of the world)
for installation in the new Woolworth Building, now
in course of construction at Broadway and Park Place.
New York.
Since this is to be the tallest building at present
erected in the world, requiring the highest elevators ever
built, the elevator equipment in this building is neces
sarily extensive and stupendous. It requires a battery
3-1 elevators to take care of the business that will be
conducted in this immense area of floor space.
As an example of the engineering ingenuity
shown in this installation four of the elevators
rise from the first to fifty-first floor a per
pendicular elevation of (579 feet (I inches.
This is the most remarkable elevator installa
tion ever conceived and built.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1914-01-04/ed-1/?sp=21&amp;q=New+York+skyscraper</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>CITY'S FIRST SKYSCRAPER NOW BEING RAZED
Original Steel Frame
Building Lasted Only
Twenty-six Years but
Gave to New York
Pattern for AH Its
Great Structures
WKUCKKRS will finish within a
few daya taking down Now
York's first skyscraper. It Is
ISO feet high, l'luus Were
placed on Hie with the Bureau of
Jtullcllnc? last week for the proponed
lii-il(l:im of thu Pan-American Htntcs
A- elation to occupy n whole block
and to he SOI feet high, or CO feet
burlier than tho Woolworth tower,
illicit now hold; tho recorder height
among t buildings of tho world. It is
jie-t twenty-six years since the city was
thrilled hy tho announcement of n high
building to be erected under a new plan
of must ruction in which a steel frame
formed an essential part, and manv wero
the predictions of its failure. Nobody in
thrilled today by tho I'an-Americaii
building plans, for they mark a Htep only
toward th-j 1.0! foot building which
everyone believe it bound to come unless
th municipal authorities take action soon
on pe proposed height limitation.
Th story of thu old Tower llulldltiK is
cii of the best illnt nitiotiM that tan be
siven of the rapidity with which New
Vork city has moved during the last
quarter century. It e.une as an expert-1
ment caiinKl success in spite of general
ridicule hikI fhnllv formed a beginning
for nil high buildings of recent time.
Now it has outlivd its usefulness. It
cannot compete, with tho giants of its
own family r.nd, like all ancestors, it is
to be laid away in lt grave, which in this
caw is thu second hand material man's
yard
Steel frame buildings like the Tower
Iluikling and the Columbia Uuildiug,
which followed it two years InteV, re
Milted from the generally lecognlzed
Advantages of buildings higher than tho
live or six story otructures that prevailed
up to the last quarter of tho last century.
The Chicago lire had taught tho danger
of nun-llreproof buildings, and here in
Nr fork builderj felt tliat structures of
sucn height that firemen could not com
bat llres on upper stories would bo but
poor investments. It was at a time while
such ideas were uppermost in the minds
of. men lnj.eret.ted in tlm upbuilding of
New York that Iir.ulford l. Oilbert filed
the plans for the Tower Building at !o
llroadway
Up to about lfe'O low buildings had been
tho rulo also because of tho imperfection
of tho elevator. Up to that year there
wero few passenger elevators in the city.
The first elevators wero oporatcd by
contrivances which would attract as much
notice in this day as then. There wero
(treat iron screws which reached tho
rdiolo height of tho elevator well, passing
thiough the centre of the cars in a steel
sleeve The turning of tho screw raised
ur lowered thu cars. Tho elevators, ,wero
slow but Nife.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87065501/1904-05-28/ed-1/?sp=6&amp;q=new+york+city+skyscrapers</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88064299/1921-02-11/ed-1/?sp=3&amp;q=new+york+city+skyscrapers</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1914-04-18/ed-1/?sp=19&amp;q=new+york+city+skyscrapers</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>THE LEANING TOWER;
Kc'jiy Tall Buildings Are Known to
Be Considerably Oat
of Plumb.
fcVvera! of New York city's skyscrapers
a?v away out of plumb and have a tend
ency to emulate the famous leaning
tower of Pisa, according to the engineer
ing department of the building bureau.
This statement should not be consider
ed remarkable in view of the recent re
port of the superintendent of buildings j
in Chicago to the effect that man> of j
the immense buildings and skyscrapers i
of the downtown district of that city are j
away out of plumb. This, according to
Building Progress, calls attention to a j
peculiarity of tall buildings little realized
and still less understood outside of the j
architectural and engineering professions.
The common impression is that all j
heavy and massive structures are rigid, t
firm and immovable; yet in Chicago, ac-
cording to the department of buildings, f
they have not one. but scores of build- j
ings like the leaning tower of Pisa, only j
they do not lean so much, thirty inch'**
being the most that any of them are j
o?.:t of plumb.
Have Two Movements.
So far from being perfectly firm and
rigid, all tall buildings are subject to
two uistiuct movements, and all heavy
buildings erected en anything but bed
rock have three distinct movements.
The city of Chicago, built as it is on
substrata of clay, furnishes the most j
interesting study of the movement of j
buildings, and the greatest number and
ity of examples. All of the early
skyscrapers of that city u?-re carried
on floating foundations, or on piles I
driven d*-ep into the clay.
These buildings, without exception, set-
led into the soil, due to their weight.
he distances they settled varying from
nree to over five inches. Many of these!
buildings are partly carried on jacks and
periodically leveled up as settlements oe- j
ur: then, after all subsidence has taken
?j ace and the buildings have finally come j
o rest, the jacks are removed and the I
foundation walls filled in with masonry.1
On Floating Foundations.
That is one of the movements of build- j
ings. then, settlement; but settlement'!
:akes place only in those buildings erect
ed on floating foundations. When the
footings are extended down to bedrock,
is all footings for present-day buildings
,n Chicago are. the amount of settlement
ihat takes place Is nil and may be dis
regarded.
But even buildings with their footings
rarried to bedrock lean or are racked out
2>f plumb and the taller the building the
more they are likely to lean, although
the amount they are out of plumb is sel
Som enough to endanger the structure.
Recently the building commissioner ot
Chicago ordered the Unity building
itraightened. as it was "unsafe, but not
3angerou8." being thirty inches out of
plumb. In an interview he said; "It is
jnpossible to prevent the big buildings</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038485/1905-09-24/ed-1/?sp=21&amp;q=new+york+city+skyscrapers</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>GREAT HIGH BILL
IT COB ISLAND
An Architectural Freak Soon to
be Started
WILL IE HUGE STRUCTURE
Aerial Globe Wai First Proposed for
St. Louis Fair and Will Be 700
Feet High—Some of
the Features.
From the New York World.
Can you imagine an entire block of
New York city skyscrapers lifted into
the air to an altitude equalling their own
great height,' and supported there on
iron legs? If so, you can conceive of a
coming wonder at Coney Island—the
greatest wonder not only of that place of
startling and majestic freaks, but of its
kind the most stupendous wonder of all
the world.
Coney Island is to have the aerial globe,
once planned as the greatest attraction
of the St. Louis World’s Fair.
Work will begin on this vast structure
next month, according to present plans.
It will be completed in time for next
season’s opening.
Regardless of the respect due to its
unique majesty, this gigantic construction
will be known, in popular designation,
as ’’Coney’s High Ball,"
The aerial globe will be 700 feet high—
twice the height of the tallest building
In this city.
The steel globe Itself will have a diam
eter of 360 feet. Its ^circumference will ex
ceed that of the Madison Square Garden.
To build this structure will cost 51,
000,000.
In its Interior 25,000 persons can at one
time llnd entertainment. The seating ca
pacity of Its halls, theatres, restauraius
and observation towers will be more than
the combined seating capacity of the
live greatest halls and theatres of this
city—the Madison Square Garden, the
Hippodrome, the Metropolitan opera
house, the Academy of Music and the
New York theatre.
In Its sub-structure this colossal edifice
will be a railway terminal—a station with
ten tracks and five double platforms, each
36 wide and 360 feet long. From the cen
ter of this great subway depot eight elec
tric elevators, each with a capacity of
sixty persons, will ascend Into the dome.
Will Have Great Speed.
These elevators will have a speed of
600 feet a minute, and they will all be
“expresses,” ascending without stopping
to the top of tlie great steel edifice. From
there passengers can descend, at their
leisure, to the halls within the globe,
by elevators and escalators.
One hundred and fifty feet above the
ground is the first great hail, to be known
as the pedestal roof garden. Here will
be a vaudeville theatre with continuous
performances, and restaurants. On the
floor are seats for 5000 persons. In a
suspended mezzanine floor, are kitchens
and lavatories.
The next amusement floor above this
is in the globe itself. Three hundred and
fifty feet above the ground a great space
will be devoted to the aerial coliseum and
hippodrome, with a seating capacity al
most identical with that of the hippodrome
in this city—5000 persons. This great hall
is 1000 feet in circumference. A continu
ous circus will occupy its four rings or
stages, three of which will be visible to
every spectator. The seats will rise in
tiers and behind and above them at the
outer rim of the globe there will be a
promenade thirty-five feet wide. From
this promenade a magnificent view out
of doors can be obtained through the
glass surrounding the done at this point,
or, looking inward, down into the coli
seum.</text>
      </result>

      <result>
	<id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1951-04-20/ed-1/?sp=5&amp;q=new+york+city+skyscrapers</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
      </result>

    </results>
  </topic>


</topics>
